<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A most necessary &amp; frutefull dialogue, betwene [the] seditious libertin or rebel Anabaptist, &amp; the true obedient christia[n] wherin, as in a mirrour or glasse ye shal se [the] excellencte and worthynesse of a christia[n] magistrate: &amp; again what obedience is due vnto publique rulers of all th[os]e [that] professe Christ yea, though [the] rulers, in externe &amp; outward thinges, to their vtter dampnatyon, do otherwyse then well: translated out of Latyn into Englishe, by Iho[n] Veron Senonoys.</title>
            <title>Von dem unverschampten Fräfel der Widertöuffer. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113331</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848567</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848567</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13656</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97377)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13656)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 642:04b, 876:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A most necessary &amp; frutefull dialogue, betwene [the] seditious libertin or rebel Anabaptist, &amp; the true obedient christia[n] wherin, as in a mirrour or glasse ye shal se [the] excellencte and worthynesse of a christia[n] magistrate: &amp; again what obedience is due vnto publique rulers of all th[os]e [that] professe Christ yea, though [the] rulers, in externe &amp; outward thinges, to their vtter dampnatyon, do otherwyse then well: translated out of Latyn into Englishe, by Iho[n] Veron Senonoys.</title>
                  <title>Von dem unverschampten Fräfel der Widertöuffer. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
                  <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted the third daye of Aprill. Anno. Do. 1551. At Worceter in ye hygh strete, by Ihon Oswen. They be also to sell at Shrewesbury. Cum priuligio ad imprimendum solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[Worcester] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1551]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of extracts from Bullinger's Von dem unverschampten Fräfel der Widertöuffer.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A dialogue betwene the rebell and subiect.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The Folger Shakespeare Library copy is bound with Richard Brasier's "A godly wil and confession of the Christian faythe" (STC 3552.7).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 3552a on reel 642.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 642 and at reel 876 (both Folger Shakespeare Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:13"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>¶ A moſt neceſſary &amp; frutefull Dialogue, betwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeditious Libertin or rebel Anabaptiſt, &amp; the true obedient chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherin, as in a mirrour or glaſſe ye ſhal ſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> excellence and worthyneſſe of a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magiſtrate: &amp; again what obedience is due vnto publique ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers of al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> profeſſe Chriſt yea, though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rulers, in ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terne &amp; outward thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, to their vtter dampnaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, do otherwyſe then well: tranſlated out of Latyn into Engliſſhe, by Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Veron Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nonoys.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Romaines .xiii. chapter:</bibl>
               <p>Whoſoeuer reſiſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power, reſyſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordinaunce of God, but they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reſyſt ſhal receiue to them ſelues dampnation</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:14"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The contentes of thys boke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>i That a chriſtian, contrarye to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious opynion of thanabaptiſtes or ſeditious Libertins, may lawfully exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the office of a Magiſtrate.</item>
               <item>ii That y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offyce of a Magiſtrate, is not onely profitable, but alſo moſt neceſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to a Chriſtian commune weale.</item>
               <item>iii That we are all bounde to obeye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and rulers, in externe &amp; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thinges, but if they commaund any thing againſt god, and his worde better it is to obey god then men: Yet not to reſiſte violently.</item>
               <item>iiii Whether it be lawfull to reſiſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, where we do wryte againſte them that do rebell againſt magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and rulers.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:14"/>
            <head>¶ To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right worſhipfull Syr Ihon Gates, Knight, Ihon Veron wiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſheth peace, grace, &amp; health, both of ſoule and body, with increaſe of diuine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtandynge, from god the father, throughe oure Lorde and Sauyour Ieſus Chriſte.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Allyng to remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce right worſhipfull Syr, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great inconuenyences &amp; harmes, that lately dyd chaunce to this moſt illu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtre &amp; floriſhing Realme by the diſobedient rebellyon, of certayne vngodly and wycked perſons, which ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting god and his word behind theyr bac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, did ſeke nought els, but an vtter con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſyon of all thynges: I can not but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and mourn, that yet ſo great blind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; ignoraunce doth,<note place="margin">When pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, true mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtring of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des word ſhal ceaſſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal the people be ſcattered ſaith the ſcripture.</note> for lacke of trew preachers and miniſters of goddes word (without the which beyng purely &amp; ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely preached, no trewe obedience, nor duety can be learned, whatſoeuer the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the truth do babell and prate) reygne emong the commons and inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters of this countrey, that they beinge wrapped in all kyndes of errour, do not
<pb facs="tcp:13656:15"/> knowe, nor yet vnderſtande, that to ryſe for any maner of cauſe, againſt the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates,<note place="margin">Thre thinges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rebelles do incurre by their rebellion</note> rulers &amp; high powers, is moſte dampnable too theyr ſoules, moſt paryl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe to theyr naturall countreye, and to theyr bodyes (for whoſe ſake, they, lyke brute beaſtes, ſtyrre vp all this hurly bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly) moſt hurtful and daungerous. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che three thynges, I wyll here proue by the word of god, and examples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, puttyng before theyr eyen, howe ſore god doth abhorre and deteſt al rebel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lious inſurrections and tumultes: to the intent, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they being taughte and inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted oute of goddes worde, waye leaue of and ceaſſe from theyr raſſhe and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enterpryſes.<note place="margin">Rom. xiii. cha</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rebelles doo purchaſe vnto theym ſelues euerlaſtinge dampnatyon.</note>Fyrſt and formeſt let them loke vpon the .xiii. Chapter to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romaines. Where Paule ſpeaketh after this maner: Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god: but they that reſiſt, ſhal receiue to them ſelues euerlaſting damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation. Here in theſe few wordes of the bleſſed apoſtle and choſen veſſell of god we do learne, that we ought in no wyſe to reſiſt the high power. And why? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the ordynaunce of god. Who
<pb facs="tcp:13656:15"/> can, I pray you, O brayneles Libertins reſyſt the ordynaunce of god, and eſcape vnpuniſſhed? Noo man truelye. For the holy ghoſte ſayth, that they that reſyſte, ſhall receyue to them ſelues dampnatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Thys were ynough to proue that to riſe agaynſt the hygh powers, is moſt damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable to the ſoules, excepte ſome were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge theym, moſte craftye and ſubtile whyche by and by, wyll make an obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon, and ſaye. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> Is the power of tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſe and vngodlye Prynces of God? Noo man (ſaye they) wyll ryſe agaynſt a godlye Prynce, whych without doubt is of god. But we do ryſe agaynſt moſt wicked &amp; vngodly rulers, whiche dailye do ſo ſore oppreſſe vs, that we can ſuffer noo longer, excepte we and oure chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll go hereafter a beggyng. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwere or ſolutyon. </seg>
               </label> To whom we doo aunſweare wyth Saynct Paule There is noo power but of God. All the powers that bee, are ordeyned of God. Syth then that there is no power but of God, it foloweth by good conſequence that the tyrannycal power is of god, and that whoſoeuer doth reſiſt it,<note place="margin">The tiranny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call power is of god, as peſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tylence, hayle vnſeaſonable wethers, &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lyke pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues.</note> doth reſyſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordinaunce of god, therby purchaſing vnto him ſelfe euerlaſting dampnatyon.
<pb facs="tcp:13656:16"/> But I will tell the howe the tyrannicall power is of god, euen as peſtilence, haile vnſeaſonable weathers, and other lyke plagues, which are by the righteous iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement of god, ſente vpon vs, for our ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. Whiche thinge we maye well ſe of Pharao in Hieremy,<note place="margin">Eſai. iij. chap</note> and of Sennache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib, kyng of the Aſſirians, in Eſaie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete, yea, the lord ſaith him ſelfe: I will geue chyldiſſhe men to be your Princes and gouernours, ſcornefull or womanly or effeminate perſons ſhall beare rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Mark ye this oh rebelles, &amp; acknowledge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, are a rod ſent of god, to puniſh youre ſynnes.</p>
                  <p>The lord doth make the wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked to reygne for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes of the people.</p>
               </note> Ye ſhal alſo be pilled and polled and one ſhall euer be doing violence and wronge to an other. The boye ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume againſt the elder, and the vyle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon agaynſt the honorable. And whye? Becauſe that both your wordes &amp; your counſailes are againſte the lorde, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke the preſence of his maieſtye, vntoo anger. By theſe wordes of the holy pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete, it is eaſy to vnderſtande, that oure ſynnes are the chief cauſes why y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde god aboue, doth ſende vngodly and wyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked rulers. But thys, we will not ſe nor heare, our eyen are ſo fixed vpon the faul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the high powers, and gouernours that we do vtterlye forget our owne, we
<pb facs="tcp:13656:16"/> can eſpie a mote in theyr eye,<note place="margin">Mat. vij. cha It is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertye of fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhneſſe too forget hys owne, and to ſe other men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſynnes.</note> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beam that is in oure owne, that wyll we not ſe We blame them for couetouſnes, &amp; wee our ſelues, are an hundreth tymes more couetouſe in our heartes, then they are, we blame them for theyr pryde, and no man is ſo proud, ſo high mynded, ſo ſtub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>burne &amp; hawte of corage, as we are oure ſelues, we blame them for theyr gay ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, and coſtly fare, and we our ſelues if we were as able as they, woulde go a thouſand tymes more gay, &amp; fare a thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſand tymes more coſtly then they doo. I do appele to your own conſciences, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther it be not ſo as I ſay. Truly though ye diſſemble neuer ſo muche,<note place="margin">Pſalme. vij.</note> and clooke that poiſon that lieth hidden in your her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, neuer ſo craftely, yet almighty God which is the ſearcher of the heartes, and of the loynes, knoweth what beaſte ye nouryſſhe and beare aboute with you in your heartes. Which thyng ſhall be ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt and open,<note place="margin">How we mai deliuer our ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues from miſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry and calami<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lord ſhal reuyſe the ſecretes of euery mans hearte. Wyll ye then be rydde from the myſerye that ye are wrapped in? Will ye be deliuered from extorcion, tyrannie and oppreſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Remoue and put awaye the cauſes. Let
<pb facs="tcp:13656:17"/> vs put awaye theſe enorme ſynnes, that we are drowned in, I meane, vnfayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, murmurynge agaynſte GOD, ingratytude and vnthankefulneſſe. Let vs banyſſhe from emonge vs vncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, fornycatyon, adulterye, dronken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, backbytynge periurye, vntrue dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, vnlawfull othes, and blaſphemous ſwearynges. Thys done, let vs boldelye flye vntoo the Lorde, and wyth earneſte prayers, procedynge from a trewe and an vnfayned faythe, call vpon hym for ayde and ſuccoure, and wythout doubte he wyll heare vs. For the truthe it ſelfe dyd ſaye:<note place="margin">Pſalme. l.</note> Call vpon me in the day of thy trouble, and I wyll bothe heare and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer the, that thou mayeſt gloryfye my name. Marke thys well, he dothe notte ſaye: In thy trouble, that is to ſay, when thou art afflycted and oppreſſed, runne into the fyelde, and there mutter, &amp; make vnlawfull aſſembles agaynſte the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, but he ſayth. Call vpon mee, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng a moſt comfortable promyſe, that he wyll bothe heare and delyuer thee.</p>
            <p>Seeke then the meanes that the Lorde hath appoynted the, and folowe not thy carnall and fleſſhelye affectyons, for
<pb facs="tcp:13656:17"/> they are blynde,<note place="margin">Carnal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="7 letters">
                     <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly affec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> are blynde.</note> and wyll brynge the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too all kyndes of calamytye and myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, whereas yf thou doeſt obeye god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde, and ſuffer pacyentelye the wronge, if any were done vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, by the hyghe powers and rulers, thou mayeſt be ſure that he wyll deliuer the at length thoughe it be not ſo ſoone, as thou wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt haue it. For it is wrytten.<note place="margin">Pſalme. ix.</note> The poor ſhall not be forgotten alwayes, the pacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ente abydynge of the meke, ſhall not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe for euer. Oh, that thys doctryne were prynted in all mennes heartes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhoulde we haue leſſe tumulte and ſedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon,<note place="margin">Tumult &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition dothe come of plain ignoraunce of gods worde.</note> whych truely doth ryſe of nothing elles: but of playne ignoraunce of gods worde, and heauenlye truthe. Were not the chyldren of Iſrael, the choſen and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected people of God, a longe ſeaſon in Egipt, beyng by the ſpace of foure ſcore yeres and more, ſo ſore afflycted and op<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſed by that cruell tyraunte Pharao,<note place="margin">Exo. i.ii. cha.</note> that beſydes all other myſeryes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth they were there ouerwhelmed, they were fayne to ſe all theyr men chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren as ſoone as they were borne, too be kylled afore theym, or elles before theyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yen, to be drowned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riuer of Nilus?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:18"/>
            <p>And yet we doo not reade, nor heare, though they were ſix hundreth thouſand men, beſides women and chyldren, that there was euer anye mutteryng, any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or vnlawfull aſſembles emong them;<note place="margin">Exo. xiiij. cha.</note> but dyd abyde ſtyll pacientlye the helpynge hande of the Lorde, whiche at lengthe, when they did call earneſtly vp on hym, dyd deliuer them ſo mightely, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> without any ſweard drawing they were reuenged of their enemyes, whyche op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed them. Let vs doo the ſame, let vs abyde paciently the helpyng hande of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, let vs put away vice, and embrace vertue,<note place="margin">Praiers are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> armure &amp; wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians in afflic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. Pſalme. ix.</note> callyng night and day vpon oure heauenly father. (For praiers are the ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mour and weapons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtians, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are in affliction and trouble) &amp; wee maye be ſure that he wyll not forget vs, the holy Prophete Dauid, ſaying: God forgetteth not the complaynt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore But yf we go about, by vnlawfull mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and wayes, to delyuer our ſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſydes that we ſhall runne (as the late ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience taughte vs) intoo farther thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and bondage, we ſhall without all doubt, purchaſe vnto oure ſelues, euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng dampnatyon. For why? We doo
<pb facs="tcp:13656:18"/> reſyſt the ordynaunce of god. Which to do is moſt dampnable, as the holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth teſtifye.<note place="margin">Rebelles goo aboute too bring their na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turall cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey to vtter deſola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon. Mat. xij. chap</note>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe let vs ſe intoo what parell and ieopardye, theſe brayneles and vngodly folkes, do moſt vnnaturally bryng theyr own natural countrey. Do not they, as much as in them lyeth, by theyr ſedity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tumulte, go about to bryng it to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſolatyon? Chriſt our ſauyoure, the euerlaſtyng wiſedome of the father, and eternall truth, ſayth: Euery kyngdome deuided agaynſt it ſelfe, ſhall be brought to naughte. And euerye Citie deuided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt it ſelfe, ſhall not ſtande. Wherby it may be gathered, that they that ſeke or make anye diuiſion within a Realme or countrey, do intend nothing els (though they falſly pretende an other thyng) but to brynge the ſame Realme or countrey to naught. It is vnpoſſyble that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of our ſauyour, whych is the truthe it ſelfe, ſhuld be falſe. Whych to be moſt true and infallible,<note place="margin">What Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mun weales didde fall to decaye by dyuyſyon</note> daily experience doth ſuffycyently teache vs. For, what thing I pray, did bryng the floryſſhynge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune weale of the Aſſirians to naught? Diuiſion. What thing did make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,
<pb facs="tcp:13656:19"/> Perſians, and almoſte all Aſia, ſoo weake, that they could not withſtande a handfull that came out of Macedonia? Diuiſion. What thinge did ſubuert and turne vpſide downe, that goodlye and well ordered common weale, of the Lace<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demonians, whych in vertue and manly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes dyd farre excede all other men? Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion. What thyng did bring the Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienſes, which were rulers of al Grecia and lordes of the ſeas, to ſo greate thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſeruitude and bondage, that they could neuer get them ſelues into libertie agayne? Diuiſion. What hath broughte the Romaynes, whyche by theyr pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſſe, had conquered al the wholl world into ſoo baſe a ſtate, that the leſſe kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Europa, is able too compare w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, whyche afore made all the wholl world to tremble and quake at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dynt of their ſword? Diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. To be ſhort, what thyng did in tymes paſſe, encourage the Danes and Normans, too inuade thys countrey, almoſt to the vtter vndoynge and confuſyon of thys noble and floryſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing Realme? Diuiſion. That I ſhould in the meane ſeaſon let paſſe, and ſpeake nothynge of the common weale of the
<pb facs="tcp:13656:19"/> Iewes and Iſraelites, whiche after that they were ones deuyded agaynſte them ſelues, were neuer able to reſyſt theyr e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemyes. In ſo muche, that at lengthe, they were brought into perpetuall capti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitye and thraldome. Read the holy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, reade Ioſephus, Herodotus, Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Titus Liuius, Sabellicus, and for the hiſtoryes of Englande, Polydorus, Virgilius. Ye may ſe nowe that by ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng vp of diuiſion, ye did brynge your owne naturall countrey, into as great a paryll as myghte be.<note place="margin">God was the defender of this realme in the tyme of inſurrction.</note> For onleſſe God had beene a ſtronge Bulwarke, vntoo thys moſte victorious Realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, and a moſte fauourable father, pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tectoure, and defendoure vntoo oure Virgyn kynge, (for whoſe ſake onelye thoughe all thinges, yea and your owne liues had bene taken from you, ye ought to haue ſuffered, and too haue refrayned from ſuche deueliſſhe enterpriſes) it had beene vnpoſſyble but the forenne naty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hadde come vpon vs. Prayſe and lande bee gyuen vntoo the for euer, O mercyfull father, that thou dyddeſte of thy mere mercye, wythoute anye de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeruynges or demerites of ours, preſerue
<pb facs="tcp:13656:20"/> our illuſtre and noble kyng, with all hys dominions and Realms, in this moſt pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rillous tyme of inſurrectyon and tumult which theſe children of Belial, dyd ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly ſtyrre vp. For what wyll ye haue vs to call you? Good felowes? Maynte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners and defenders of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common weal?<note place="margin">Why I was loth at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt that theſe tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult &amp; inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectyon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, ſhuld be called rebels and traitours</note> By lykelyhode ye woulde be ſoo called Nay, nay, I was full loth at the fyrſt (I haue many to bear me record of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame) that ye ſhould be called rebelles or tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, becauſe I thoughte thoſe names to be to heynouſe for you. Agayn, I had a good hope that ye would be wonne, &amp; reclamed by ſome fayre and gentle mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. (For who would haue thoughte ſo muche ſtubburneſſe in you?) Farther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, I was afrayd that your rageouſe madnes ſhoulde rather be ſet on fyre by ſuche wordes, then aſſwaged. It was, I ſay, ſore agaynſt my wyll, that ſo horry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and odyouſe names, ſhould be giuen vnto you at the fyrſt: but ſyth now that ye dyd perſyſt, and ſome of you doo yet furyouſly perſyſt in geuyng the occaſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſuche moſt deuilyſh interpryſe, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing perſwaded by noo maner of reaſon: What may we ryghtly call you, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles
<pb facs="tcp:13656:20"/> and traytours, and moſt extreame enemyes of the commune weale? For, all that ye go about, is to vndo this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and floryſſhyng Realme, and moſte vnnaturally to betray your owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall countrey, vnto forenne nations and Princes. I ſay vnto you, that all youre mortall enemyes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> compaſſe you round about (ſet them all together, Frenchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Scottes, Danes, Turkes) culd not haue founde or ymagined a more ready waye to deſtroy Englande, then ye Englyſhe men dyd. For as a Realme, be it neuer ſo ſmall, is inuincible, yf the ſubiectes of it, beyng knitted in loue, do holde toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſo, if they be once deuided agaynſte them ſelues, it is vnpoſſyble, but that the ſame lande &amp; countrey,<note place="margin">Scilurus king of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scitians.</note> muſt be brought to vtter deſolation. Whych thyng Scilu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rus, a Kynge of the Scitians, did moſte liuely ſet furth, by a goodlye exaumple &amp; Apophthegme, which I woulde it were bothe written and paynted vpon euerye wall, that men myghte learne thereby how ſtrong a thing concord and vnytye is. This kinge,<note place="margin">Maruail not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thys kynge had ſo many ſonnes, for it was lawfull vnto them, to get childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on many wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> as the hiſtories do teſtify had .lxxx. ſonnes, whom a litle afore hys deathe, he dyd call altogether, biddynge
<pb facs="tcp:13656:21"/> them, to bryng euery one of them an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe. Whych thing beyng done, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded that all the arowes ſhoulde be faſt bounde together, and ſo delyuered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bondell of arowes, beyng thus faſt bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to euery one of his ſonnes, bydding the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to breake the arowes, as they were faſte bounde together in one bondell. Which thynge, becauſe it was vnpoſſyble, they refuſed to doo. Then the kyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the arowes to be vnbounde, and did geue to euery one of them an arowe too breake, whyche they did lightely. Then the kyng exhorting his ſonnes to vnitye and concord, did ſaye to them after thys maner:<note place="margin">By concorde ſmall thynges do growe, but by diſcorde great thinges are broughte to naughte.</note> If ye agre wythin youre ſelues, and holde together, ye ſhal be inuincible no man ſhall be able too ouercome you, but if ye diſagre and fal out emong your ſelues, ye ſhall be both weake and eaſye to be ouercomen. Shall not this heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ethnike kinge, riſe in the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; condempne you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo vngodly do breake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnitye, peace and concorde of your owne naturall countrey? Oh how many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathen, which neither knew god, nor his word, did offer them ſelues manfully to die for the welfare &amp; preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatyon
<pb facs="tcp:13656:21"/> of their owne naturall contrey, &amp; theſe vnreaſonable beaſtes (to call them chriſtians, I am aſhamed) do go aboute and ſtudy all that they can to deſtroye it, to betraye it, and moſte trayterouſlye to bryng it to naught. Oh what may I ſay now vnto you?</p>
            <p>Repente for goddes ſake, and come to your ryght mynd againe, for yf ye go on thus by vnlawfull meanes to ſhake of &amp; put away the plague and ſcorge, that god hath ſente to you, for your deteſtable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, beſides euerlaſting dampnation, and vtter vndoing of your own naturall con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey,<note place="margin">Rebelles doe alwaies come to a ſhamefull ende, &amp; death of their body<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es.</note> ye ſhal incurre a moſt ſhameful deth of your bodies. Reade all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hiſtories both prophane and holy, that euer were write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſince the begynnyng of the world, and ye ſhal your ſelfes fynd, that alwaies rebels haue had a ſhamefull ende. And no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile, for they do reſiſte the ordinaunce of god. I myghte here repete and reherce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyſtory of Corah,<note place="margin">Num. xvi. cha</note> Dathan and Abyram which with their wiues and children and xiiii. M, and .dcc, that held with them, did horrybly peryſhe for theyr rebellyon,<note place="margin">Iudi. xii. chap</note> I myght allege how Ephraim made inſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection againſt Iephtha, whom god had
<pb facs="tcp:13656:22"/> raiſed to be iudge ouer Iſrael, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which Ephraites .xlii. M. were miſerably ſlain? What nede I to bringe here the horrible tragedie of Abſalon,<note place="margin">ii Reg. xviii. chapiter.</note> and of Siba, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of Bocheri. Loke ye your ſelues vpon the bookes of the kinges, and of Paralip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomenon,<note place="margin">ii. Reg. xx. cha</note> or Chronycles, and ye ſhall there fynde, that the one beinge hanged vp by the lockes of hys heares in an oke, was thriſted thorough with .iii. ſpares, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whome .xx. M. of the people were ſlaine and loſte, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the other beyng purſued by Ioab, and beſyeged wythin Abel and Bethmaaka, was by the councell of a wiſe woman beheaded &amp; his heade thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen ouer the wal to Ioab. Dyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people therfore, that rebelled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym, eſcape vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed?<note place="margin">ii. Reg. xxiiii. chapiter.</note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> No, no, The lord god hater of all rebellion &amp; tumult, did afterwardes ſo ſore plague Iſrael w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> peſtilence, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in three daies, ther dyed .lxx. M. But y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wilt ſay: This was becauſe that Dauid had num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of Iſraell and Iuda, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
               </label> &amp; had not obſerued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe. Let the ſcripture an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for me, which ſaith. And again the lord was wroth againſt Iſrael, &amp; moued Dauid againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Al eccleſiaſtical writers do agre, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this was for the ſynne of rebe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Siba,
<pb facs="tcp:13656:22"/> rebelled againſt Dauid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> annointed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord. Oh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the ſame noble Hiſtoriograph Ioſephus, were traunſlated in to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe, for your ſakes. There, there, ſhould ye reade &amp; ſe, how many. M. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes were diſconfited, ouer throwen and ſlayn at ſundry tymes, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they rebelled againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romaines. But what nede we ſtraunge and forenne examples?<note place="margin">We maye lerne at home how rebels do ſpede.</note> we may learne at home, how they ſpede euer, that reſiſt the ordinaunce of god takyng moſt vngodly vpon them ſelues, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinge whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che belongeth only to the lord &amp; to his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted. Sith then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god doth puniſh ſo greuouſly al rebels, here in this world, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fyer from heauen, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> peſtilence &amp; ſword &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other world w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euerlaſting tormentes of hell: any childe may ſe and vnderſtand how ſore god doth deteſt and abhorre all rebellyon. Therfore if ye tender the helth of your own ſoules, if ye tender y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weal of your own natural countrey, yf ye tender your bodies, &amp; liues leaue of betimes, ceaſe from ſuch deuilliſh enterpriſes, &amp; in thys your trouble &amp; afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which doubtleſſe doth happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto you eyther for your ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes or elſe for a tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al of your faith &amp; pacie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence) call vpon the Lorde with a contryt heart, and he wyll (be ye ſure therof
<pb facs="tcp:13656:23"/> For he hath ſo promyſed) eyther molyfy the hearts of thoſe tirantes, that oppreſſe you, that they ſhall be very fathers vnto you, or elſe he wil ſhortly root the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, &amp; put into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hertes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> powers, to ſhorte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their armes,<note place="margin">Oure godlye yonge kynge whiche maye wel be compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red wyth that godlye kinge Ioſias, ſhall ſhortlye dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his people from extortio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> &amp; to rule his electe people wyth iuſtyce &amp; equytye, Beare a while thinke not longe, we haue a moſte godly Prince toward, which w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in a ſhort ſpace, ſhal comfort vs, as concerning our ſorowfull trouble and afflictyon, he ſhall wede out of hys Realme and dominions with the ſwerde of equitie, al thoſe bloud ſuckers, that now, as gredy horſleches do ſucke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of his people, &amp; louing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, in the meane ſeaſon, quiet, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryfye your ſelues, &amp; let euery man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to his vocation, laboure to lyue tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in this world, to the mayntenaunce of the common weale. Geue no more occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tender loue of god, which ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he gaue his only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne for vs, geue no more occaſion I ſaye, by your vnquiet behauiour to theſe worlde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges, to blaſpheme the goſpell &amp; word of god.<note place="margin">All tumultes and inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, are layde vpon goddes word, and the miniſters ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of.</note> Do ye not both heare and ſe, that al the inſurrections tumultes and ſedity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue now chaunced in our tymes
<pb facs="tcp:13656:23"/> are by them adſcribed and layd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of god (which by ſome of them is called new lernyng) &amp; the miniſters therof? Ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely it hadde bene better for you, to haue bene caſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> milſtones aboute your necke into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea, &amp; there to haue bene drowned, then by your ſedycious tumul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, to haue miniſtred ſuch an occaſion of offence: for ſayth the truth it ſelfe: Wo,<note place="margin">Mat. xviii. ch</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, euerlaſting dampnation han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manne, by whom the offence doth come. This one thyng (if we were trewe chriſtians) ſhuld be enough to fray vs from all vprores and inſurrections.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Obiection.</label> But me thinke I heare yet ſome emong you which do grudge and ſaye. Who in this world, were he neuer ſo pacient, could refrayne hym ſelfe, for beſydes the many folde wronges, that we ſuffer dayly and hourely by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they do ſo bitterly reuile vs, at eueri ſecond word moſt deſpitfully calling vs peyſauntes, and vilaines, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man can holde hys handes from theym. Whom I am compelled to anſwer after thys maner. Are ye Chryſtans, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
               </label> or not (I knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf any man ſhuld ſay vnto you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye are no chriſtians, ye wold be angrye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him) Yf ye are chriſtians that is to ſay
<pb facs="tcp:13656:24"/> the diſciples of Chriſt, do ye not thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is enough, and ſufficyent for you, to be as your maiſter?<note place="margin">Math. x, cha-</note> But they dyd call your maiſter and ſauioure, Belzebub, whiche is a thouſand times worſe,<note place="margin">Theſe .ii. wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des Payſant and Villayne are trewly &amp; accordinge to the right ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifycatyon of them expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> then Payſant or Villayne, whiche wordes if they were well vnderſtanded, are nothyng at all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochfull. Here in thys matter, plaine ig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noraunce doth blynd you. For payſaunt beynge deriued of this laten worde, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganus,</hi> dothe properly betoken in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſh, a man of the countrey, or that dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lethe in villages or vplande. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other word, Vilayn doth alſo come of this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, vocable, <hi>Villanus,</hi> and ſignifyeth none other thinge, in our mother and vulgaire tongue, but a fermer, or fearme holder, or elſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dwelleth in villages. Lo good peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple theſe be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reuilyng &amp; oprobrious wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des for the which ye do ſtyrre vp al theſe enorme, and greuous tragedies. But go to what &amp; if they were, the moſt reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wordes that euer could be ſpoken w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mouthe: or thought with heart (howe be it to tell the verye truthe, I woulde that theſe frenche tearmes hadde bene lefte to the french men, and that he that brought them fyrſt ouer into Englande, thereby
<pb facs="tcp:13656:24"/> to offende hys weake brethren, had bene better aduyſed) oughte yee not to haue borne them pacyently for hys ſake why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che for your ſaluation, and helth of your ſoules, dyd beſydes all kyndes of ygno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minie, opprobriouſnes and reproche, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the moſt cruell and ſhamefulleſt death that euer in thys world coulde be ymagi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned or thought.<note place="margin">Anabaptiſtes and Libertius doo alwayes boſte &amp; crake of their perfec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion. </note> Trulye ye wold be lothe to ſuffer death for hys ſake, ſythe that ye can not abyde wordes. Where is nowe that perfectyon, that ſome of you do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſe to boaſte and crake of emonge the ſymple and ignoraunte people.</p>
            <p>
               <label>A dygreſſion</label> Heare, muſt I ſomewhat digreſſe from my purpoſe, and declare what kynde of people they be that make thys buſyneſſe and ſtyrre vp contention in thys Realme and common weale.<note place="margin">The Anabap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſtes do ſeke &amp; hunte after a carnall liberty in the goſpell.</note> There be a ſorte of men whych nowe at thys preſent houre that the euaungily call doctryne, is pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and ſyncerely preached, do ſeeke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge elſe in the ſcriptures and goſpell, but a carnall and fleſhly lybertye, goyng aboute with their craftye and ſubtyll rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons and textes of the ſcriptures, halfe al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leged, to perſwade the ignoraunt people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are not bounde to obey temporall
<pb facs="tcp:13656:25"/> rulers &amp; maieſtrates. Theſe men ſyttynge vpon there ale benches, wherſoeuer they dare vtter theyr poyſon conueniently, do inculcate and beat into mens heads,<note place="margin">The errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous opynyon of the anabap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſtes, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates.</note> that no chriſtian can laufully exequute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of a maieſtrate. Which offyce of a maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate, ſay they, is neyther profytable, nor yet neceſſary to a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> common weale Wherfore, away with theſe tirantes, kyl them, rote them out of the earth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye to Chriſtes word &amp; doctrine, do moſt preſumpteouſly take vpon them, to be ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers, or rather tyrantes ouer the people of Chriſt, to whom he dyd, ſo derely, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhedyng of hys moſt precious bloud, pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaſe a perpetuall fredome and lyberty. Thys is done commonly in thoſe places where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure ſede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell,<note place="margin">
                  <p>The anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes wyll al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes come too thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, where the goſpel is prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched.</p>
                  <p>Mat. xiii. cha. The anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes &amp; Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins, do go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the magyſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes maye not kyll wyth the ſwearde.</p>
                  <p>What they be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtyrre vp commotyon, where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell is not pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched.</p>
                  <p>The oratyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papyſtes too the ſimple &amp; ignoraunte, to ſtirre them vp to tumulte &amp; commotion</p>
               </note> hath bene dyligentlye ſowen. For there the deuyll whiles men are a ſlepe, is moſte buſye to ſowe in his cockle &amp; darnel. Which wold god, it were diligently weded out by the maieſtrates and rulers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe moſt peſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferous Anabaptiſtes &amp; Libertins, mighte ones both feele and know, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do not beare the ſword, delyuered vnto them of of god, in vayne. In other places where they do yet for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt parte, ſyt in darke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:13656:25"/> of ignoraunce and ſhadow of death y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popes darlynges are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtyrers vp of al myſchief. For they, by there hypocryſye blandiloquence and flattery, are ſo farre ſunke in to mens ſtommackes, that they can eaſely perſwade them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng and al his honorable counſell, are vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, yea &amp; ſtarke heretikes. Haue they not (wyl y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhauelinges ſay to the poore ſym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple folkes of their countrey) taken away &amp; broken our godly ymages? Haue they not abolyſhed our holydayes, put doune our ceremonyes, and diſanulled the holy &amp; bleſſed Maſſe? Loke howe vnreuerent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye they do vſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed ſacrament of the Aulter. Doo they not alſo goo aboute to plucke doune all our holy Aulters. Who hauing a chriſtian harte could abide ſuch impiety, &amp; vngodlyneſſe? Come on ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neighboures, better it were for vs, to dye a thouſande deathes, then to ſe thys blaſphemy. Let vs fight for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy church &amp; rytes thereof. We may be ſure that we ſhall lyghtly ouercome theſe ranke hery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tykes. And if we chaunce to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe our ſelues (whiche thinge is not lykely, ſyth that we fyghte in gods qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell) &amp; dye in the fyeld, who wolde doubt
<pb facs="tcp:13656:26"/> but that we ſhall go ſtraighte way vp to heauen?<note place="margin">Oh falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine.</note> For Chriſt (whoſe bleſſed body and bloud, made by the holye handes of the prieſte, theſe falſe heritikes do treade vnder foot) hath ſaid,<note place="margin">Math. x. cha- Yet this texte as all other is falſely aleged of them.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſoeuer loſeth his life, for hys ſake and the churche, ſhal fynde it agayne in the reſurrection of the deade. With ſuche miſtes and iuggelyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of wordes, theſe cleane fyngered ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tlemen, do vtterlye ſubuerte the mindes of the ſimple and ignoraunt people, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che elles, if they had trew paſtours, and good minyſters,<note place="margin">Yf the people had true paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toures they wlold embrace gladlye gods worde.</note> woulde wyth all meke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and due obedyence, receyue the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye doctryne, mynyſtred ſo fatherlye vntoo them, by the Kynge, and hys ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable counſayle. They woulde notte mutter, nor open their lippes againſt the kynges moſte godlye procedinges, butte would gladly wyth the other ſubiects of this realme, embrace the wholſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of their ſaluation, and acknowlege that they haue bene hetherto ledde in er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure and blyndnes,<note place="margin">Who they be that prycke the people forwardes to tumulte and inſrrection.</note> by theſe falſe Anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes and Pſeudoprophetes, whome they nowe accepte and embrace, as god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Too be ſhorte, theſe twoo ſortes of men, I mean the Libertins and papiſtes
<pb facs="tcp:13656:26"/> are they, that do pricke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people forwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des (whyche elles of theymſelues, are ready inoughe to ſuche thynges, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially now,<note place="margin">By greadye mammons.</note> that they are ſo on euerye ſide, pilled and polled) too tumultes and inſurrections, too the vtter confuſyon of them ſelues, and vndoing of this honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable countrey, and Realme.</p>
            <p>Therfore,<note place="margin">An exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates againſt the libertins &amp; Papiſtes.</note> O ye magiſtrates and rulers whom god hath appointed ouer his cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen and elected people, with the ſwearde of equitie, to defende the widdowes and fatherles, to maintain y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good and righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous, and to puniſſhe the euil and wicked doers: it is your parte and duetye to ſeke oute ſuche runne agates, and withoute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fauoure or mercye, to punyſſhe them that all other may take example by them Put away in this caſe all foliſh pitie: for as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men prouerbe is, foliſh pytye le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countrey, &amp; beſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, better it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ii. or .iii. be thus extremely puniſhed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thouſands,<note place="margin">All foolyſhe pitye is to be ut awaye.</note> ſhould through their wycked counſails &amp; entiſements, moſt miſerably and to the great loſſe of the countrey, pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſſhe. Picke out theſe rauenynge wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and for goddes ſake, fauour the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple as muche as may be, haue that noble
<pb facs="tcp:13656:27"/> capteyn Ioab alwaies before your eyen whych as ſone as that trayterous rebell Abſalon, was by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteous iudgmente of god,<note place="margin">ii. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xviii. Chapter.</note> moſt ſhamefully ſlayne, dyd by &amp; by blowe to the retrayte, and commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to ſpare the people. Do the ſame and ye ſhal hyghly pleaſe god. Call ye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pore vnto you, and heare their complayntes paciently, o ye gods (for, ſo the ſcripture dothe call you, becauſe that ye are in the ſtede and roume of god) here ye the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnte of the poore (I ſaie) and redreſſe thoſe thynges that are amyſſe. Know of them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſes, why they are now contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye to their old wont and cuſtom, <note place="margin">An apte ſimili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude.</note> ſo bent to inſurrectyon and tumult. Yf a phiſyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wold go about to heale any diſeaſe or ſyckeneſſe, and not ſerche out the cauſes therof, wolde not all men, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> by good ryght, call him an vnkunning phiſition. The whole body of the common weale is ſore ſicke, it canne in no wiſe be healed except the cauſe of this diſeaſe and ſycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, be bothe ſearched out dilygentlye, and taken awaye. Suffer no longer, the louynge ſubiectes of thys moſte victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous countrey, whych by our moſte ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereygne Lorde the kynge, are commyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:13656:27"/> vnto your charge, cuſtodye and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectyon (Verelye it is you whyche be heare in the earthe lyeutenauntes and vicayrs of god,<note place="margin">The magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes are Gods vycares in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earthe.</note> that ſhoulde reuenge the wronges and iniuries of the people) too be eaten and ſwalowed vp, by theſe gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye Cormorauntes, which neuer beynge contente till they haue the deuill brought to them in a ſacke, ioyne houſe, to houſe, lande to lande (but woo be to them, ſaith the prophet) although they ſhould dwel alone vpon the earthe,<note place="margin">Eſai. v. Chap</note> One of them hath a thouſande mens liuinges in hys hands and yet can he ſcantelye ſuffer his poore neighbour to dwell in a poore cotage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides hym. All that he hath is to little as longe as he ſeeth any poore man, to haue any thinge by him. What ſhould I ſaye A whole ſhiere is not enough to ſatiſfye his couetouſe and vnſaſiable minde. And why, I praye, is all thys? forſoth that he his wyfe, and his children, maye go gaye and fare dayntely. Yf he can haue that, it maketh no matter, how many thouſand do go a begginge or ſtorne for hunger by him. Ah worldlinges, worldelinges, the hande of god is ſtretched furth to plague Haue ye forgotten what the holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb facs="tcp:13656:28"/> ſaythe?<note place="margin">Hiere. vii. cha</note> Becauſe ye are from the loweſt vnto the hieſt, geuen to couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and fylthy lucre: I wyll gyue your wyues, vnto other, and your fyldes vnto ſtraungers, to poſſeſſe. Hath the lord god geuen you riches, to confound the poore therwith, to oppreſſe them, and to treade them vnder fete, and not rather to helpe and ſuccour them? Ye are not the lordes but the ſtewardes and dyſpenſatours of riches. Se the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ye be faithful in your ſtewardſhyp, or elles youre ſtewardſhyp ſhall be taken from you, and gyuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too an other. The Lorde god hath giuen you, and dothe daylye gyue you warnin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ynowe, but ye are ſoo blynded with worldelye couetouſneſſe and proſperitie that ye wyll not ſee,<note place="margin">Why the worldelinges will not take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> warnynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God giueth them daylye. Pro. xi. chap. Soph. i. chap.</note> ye are ſoo pufte vp wyth pryde and hauteneſſe of mynde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye thynke that no maner of thing in this world, can, or is able to bring you doune Marke and note therfore, what the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of God, dothe ſaye: Theyr ryches ſhall profyte them nothynge in the daye of wrathe, and he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> truſteth in hys world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye ſubſtaunce, ſhall haue a fall. Neyther theyr golde nor ſyluer ſhall, be able too delyuer theym, in the daye of the wrathe of
<pb facs="tcp:13656:28"/> the Lorde. Dothe not the exaumple of the ryche glutton, make you afrayde? Doo not hys cruell paynes and tormen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes in hell,<note place="margin">Luk. xvi. chap</note> make youre heartes to quake and tremble for feare of lyke puniſhmen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes?<note place="margin">The rich glut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton was dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, for vnmer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifulnes.</note> And yet he was dampned for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinne of vnmercifulneſſe onely. For we canne not fynde nor reade, that euer he came by hys goodes vniuſtly, or that he gatte hys ryches by hooke or crooke, as the moſte parte of you doo. Therefore loke for a thouſande times more greuous pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhementes, then he had. For not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, ye dydde not feede Chriſte, when he was an hungred, gyue hym drinke whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was a thyrſte, clothe hym,<note place="margin">Mat. xxv. cha</note> when he was naked. &amp;c. but alſo, ye did ſpoile him ye dyd pille and polle hym, ye did robbe him, and moſt tyrannouſly oppreſſe him But I know that ye will ſaye wyth the vngodly: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
               </label> when dyd we any ſuche thyng vnto Chriſte? Verelye I ſaye vnto you, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Solution. </seg>
               </label> that in ſo muche, ye dyd it too the poore neady members of Chriſte, ye dyd it too hym, and therefore ye ſhall heare that dreadfull ſentence at length: Depart ye from mee, O ye curſed creatures, intoo euerlaſtynge fyre, whyche is prepared
<pb facs="tcp:13656:29"/> for the deuill and his aungels. <label>A godly pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er.</label> O mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and heauenlye father, graunte I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche the, that all men puttyng away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their heartes, worldly couetouſenes, and pryde of mynde, wherwyth they are hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den blynde, may haue grace, to ſee howe they came into this world, and ſo too vſe the ryches, wherewith y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſt indue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> too thy glorye, and ſaluatyon of theyr ſoules.</p>
            <p>Nowe therfore, O chriſtyan magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, be ye ſtronge in the lorde, take righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes for your ſhield, &amp; weapon your ſelfes with vpright and vncorrupted iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gemente,<note place="margin">God hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore</note> and hauing the fear of the lord for youre guyde, reuenge manfullye the wronges and iniuryes of the poore (for therfore hath the lord god ordeined you) Let them both feale and knowe, that ye beare a fatherly affection towardes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that ye will not ſe them to ſuffer any ſuch vilany at theſe worldlinges handes. Se an order (for this is your duetie) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the riche maye be contente wyth the poore, and that the poore maye be ſuffered too lyue by the riche. Seke out the cauſes of this narre, that is nowe betwene the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilytie and the commens, cutte of, wyth the
<pb facs="tcp:13656:29"/> ſwerde of equitie al occaſion of ſtrife and debate,<note place="margin">The gentyll<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men, and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munes of this realme, beyng knitte in loue are a wall too the countrey</note> that the gentilmen and commons of thys Realme, being knytted in loue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, maye be as afore tymes a ſtronge bulwarke and wall vnto this moſt victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous countrey of Englande. Ye can no better deſerue of the common weale then ſo. And yf in the meane ſeaſon ye fynd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe wicked Anabaptiſtes &amp; Liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tines, or anye of thoſe obſtynate papiſtes that go about to ſubuert, ſeduce, intoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and poyſon the myndes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, perſuadyng them, that they may law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully riſe againſt theyr maieſtrates, ſpare theym not, roote oute thoſe pernicyouſe wedes from amonge the people. Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is that fewe doo peryſhe, then that all the whole countrey ſhoulde through theyr wycked perſwaſion, be brought to naught. Theſe be they that are the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blers of the common peace.<note place="margin">Math. vii. Chapter.</note> Therfore be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ware of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, O chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brethren, for they come vnto you in ſhepes clothing, but in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardly they are rauening wolfes. Truſt them not, ſuffer not your ſelues in anye wyſe to be perſuaded, that ye maye for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maner of cauſe, ryſe againſt the maieſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trates. All that they go about, is to bryng
<pb facs="tcp:13656:30"/> you to vtter confuſyon. For though the maieſtrates were come to that madneſſe impietye, &amp; vngodlynes, that they ſhuld commaund you to do thinges, contrarye to gods lawes, and his holye worde (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> marked monſters of Antichriſte,<note place="margin">Reade y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Acts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, and all whole Euſebius and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt fynd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alwayes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciples of chriſt dyd defende them ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gods worde.</note> do go aboute to make you to beleue) yet ought ye in no wiſe to reſiſte them. None other ſwerd ye haue to fyght agaynſt vngodly maieſtrates, but gods word, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame wepon ought ye alwaies to defend your ſelues, againſt all kindes of vngodlynes &amp; yet it muſt be done, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch ſobrietye &amp; manſuetude, lenitie &amp; gentlenes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alwais chriſtian lyke obedience, toward the ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce of god, ſhall ſhine &amp; apere in you. Marke now this: Yf we may not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teriall ſwerd reſiſte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maieſtrates, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence of godlines &amp; trew relygyon, what ſhall we ſay by them, which for the main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenaunce of falſe religion, do bringe all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neckes of godly maieſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes? It was not for noughte, O chriſtan rulers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the godly kynges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament when they dyd put doune Idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>try &amp; ſuperſtition, dyd ſley and kyl al the prieſtes and ſacrificators of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ydols &amp; fals gods, weding out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe prophetes from
<pb facs="tcp:13656:30"/> emonge the people to the intente, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould not bryng againe, the ſimple and ignoraunt into errour. What I do mean any man that hath wit, may vnderſtand. How be it, I wold not haue them to be put to death nor ſlaine, onleſſe they be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſtubburne and obſtacle, or go aboute ſome tumult or nouation of thinges, but I wold haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be kepte ſo ſhort tyll they depart hence in peace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might do no harme in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane ſeaſon. As for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, I mean y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Libertines &amp; Anabaptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes they ought in no wiſe to be ſpared, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept we wyll haue the countrey by their tumultes &amp; inſurrections, to be brought to vtter deſolation, Agaynſt whom, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better herafter be fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced &amp; enarmed in this point, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trew obedience toward magiſtrats &amp; rulers, I haue here traunſlated out of Laten into Englyſh .iiii. ſmall dialogues,<note place="margin">That famous clerke Bullin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; maker of theſe dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loges.</note> betwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rebell Libertin or anabaptiſte, &amp; the trew obedient chriſtian. Wherin ye ſhall learne fyrſte, that a chriſtian, contrarye to theyr moſt erroneous doctrine, may lawfully ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ecute the offyce of a maieſtrate. Second<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, that a Chriſtyan Maieſtrate is not onely profytable, but alſoo neceſſarye
<pb facs="tcp:13656:31"/> to a chriſtian common weale. Thyrdly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are bound to obey the maieſtrates in all externe and outward things. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, that we ought in no wiſe, nor for any maner of cauſe, to reſyſte the rulers &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, where we do write largelye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them, whiche rebell agaynſte the maieſtrates.</p>
            <p>Which ſmal laboure of myne, I thought no man in this cuntrey, ſo worthy to haue as your righte worſhipfull maſterſhyppe Firſt becauſe of the good reporte, that is geuen you of al the countrey about, both for the feruent zeale that ye haue to gods word, and maintenaunce of trew religion and alſo becauſe that ye vſe your ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies emong them, as a moſt louing and tender father, ſekyng not your owne pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyte, but onely the profite and welfare of them that are vnder your gouernaunce &amp; ruledome. Oh that all other gentylmen wolde imitate and folowe you, both in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thinge, and alſo in kepyng of hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie, then ſhuld we haue ſhortly a mery England. The ſecond cauſe that moueth me, to dedicate, this litle worke vnto you is that ye are by the deuine prouidence of god and the kinges maieſtie, placed in au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoritie
<pb facs="tcp:13656:31"/> for this our countrey of Eſſex, in the which, many of theſe Libertines and Anabaptiſtes, are runnyng in hoker mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, emonge the ſymple and ignoraunte people, to impell and moue theym, to tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multe and inſurrection agaynſte the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtrates and rulers of thys Realme. Whom I truſt (if ye ones knowe them) ye will ſoone wede out of the countreye, to the greate good &amp; quiet, of the kinges ſubiectes, of the ſame countye and ſhiere Nowe ryght worſhipfull Syr, though I be not knowen, nor yet acquainted wyth your maiſterſhyp, wherfore it may perad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uentur ſeme to ſome to be a bold act, or in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terpriſe for me too offer, or nuncupate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye maner of booke vnto you: yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandynge the greate facilytye and gentylnes, that all men, women and chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren do depredycate and ſaye, is in you, dothe put me in verye good hope, that ye wil take this my rude laboure in good worth. Which thinge if ye doo, hereafter paraduenture greater and more ſeryous thynges ſhall enſue, god wyllynge, who of hys infynyte mercye and bounteous goodneſſe, vouchſafe wyth his holy ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryt, ſo to rule and guide your heart, wyth
<pb facs="tcp:13656:32"/> that godlye Ladye youre trewe louynge ſpouſe and wyfe, that what ſoo euer ye ſhall do or thynke, in all your affayres maye be to the glorye of god, the common weale of the Realme and the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your ſoules. AMEN.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:32"/>
            <head>The Dialogue. That a Chriſtyan maye execute the office of a maieſtrate. The interloquutours. IOIADA the trewe and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Chriſtian, and SIMON the Libertine or Anabaptiſte.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od ſpede Simon, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> comeſt betyme, I ſe that thou art deſirous of the truth, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I haue a good hope, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhalt obteyne &amp; come by that thynge, whiche thou deſireſte ſo greately. Touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrate, where vpon, we were determined to haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, I doute not, but that I ſhall ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye the in al thinges. But tell fyrſt what thy iudgement is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>Thyne opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is that a chriſtian maye execute the offyce of a Maieſtrate, but I do thynke that both the word &amp; example of Chriſte repugneth to thys opynyon. For when they wold at a certeyn tyme chooſe him to be a kyng, he did runne awaye. Ihon vi. Which thing he wold not haue done yf it had not bene againſt all godlyneſſe. And in the .xxii. cha of Luke. Chriſt with
<pb facs="tcp:13656:33"/> expreſſed wordes ſpeketh to his diſciples after this maner: The princes of gentiles do beare rule, and they that haue power are called benefyciall, ye ſhall not ſo, but he that is greateſt emonge you, ſhal be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt, and he that is chyfeſt, ſhall be as he that myniſtreth. By theſe wordes it is manifeſte and playne, that it becommeth not chryſtyans to execute the offyce of a maieſtrate. It is lawfull for the heathen and infidels, for Chriſt ſaith. The princes of the gentiles.<note place="margin">Chriſte came to redeme the world w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys bloud.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIADA.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt came not to take awaye the publyke magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, much leſſe to execute their office, but to redeme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys bloud. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he doth runne away, not conſenting to the affections of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, for he could not haue taken vpon hym the offyce of a king, without commotion, the Romains not permitting it, which were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rulers But who euer ſo gathered his argument Chriſt was neuer a baker, ergo, no Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyan,<note place="margin">The folyſh ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gumente of the Libertins or Anabaptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> canne be a baker? Why then do ye make this argument: Chriſt neuer execu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of a maieſtrate, ergo, it is not lawfull for a chriſtyan, to be a maieſtrate or beare rule. In the .xxii. of Luke Chriſt doth warne the apoſtles of their dutye &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:13656:33"/> forbyddeth that they ſhould not be buſye in other mens matters, for they had ſtry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued by the waye, who ſhould be greateſt emonge them after the death of Chriſte. For they dyd ymagin, that there ſhoulde be ſuch a power and rule emong them, as the biſſhop of Rome hath vſurped in the latter daies in the church. He doth plucke from the minds of his diſciples this ſoure diſeaſe of ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; deſire of honor, know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge wel that this ſhould be the chief diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction of Eccleſiaſticall prelates. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he vſethe theſe wordes: The princes of nations, &amp;c. As if he ſhoulde ſay: The princes &amp; gouernours of nations, are ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poynted to rule &amp; to gouerne, as for you, ye haue an other offyce gyuen you. Yet notwithſtandyng, the offyce of a magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is not abolyſſhed by theſe words, but it may very wel ſtand by the apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyp, as it is moſt manifeſt by the words of Chriſt. But this doth begyle &amp; deceue the, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou doeſt take this word, <hi>Gentium</hi> for the heathen &amp; infideles. For they are here, by a maner of ſpeaking, called prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and kynges of nations, whyche do gouerne and bear rule in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, which power (as the apoſtles do teſtifye) is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned
<pb facs="tcp:13656:34"/> of god, whych thing Chriſt doth expreſſe by theſe words.<note place="margin">Why princes and rulers are called <hi>euerge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, beneficiall.</note> They are called <hi>Euergetae,</hi> that is to ſaye, beneficyall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that they are ordeyned to do good to them that are good &amp; vertuous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI.</speaker>
               <p>By this reaſon and meane, I maye caſt of whatſoeuer can be layde agaynſt me, oute of the ſcriptures, ſaying: This was ſaid to the apoſtles, it perteineth nothing to vs: But Chriſte teacheth vs an other thinge in the .xiii. chap, of Marke: Theſe thynges (ſayth he) that I tell you, I do tel to al. This word then, where he ſayth (But ye ſhal not do ſo) perteyneth vnto al them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are godly, and not onely to the apoſtles.<note place="margin">How y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of the .xiij. cha of Marke, oughte too be vnderſtanded.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>Thou doſt paſſe thy boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, my Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and doſt not abide in the matter that was propouned, our commu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nication is of the magiſtrate. In the .xiij. chap. of Marke, which thou doſt aledge, Chriſt doth exhort his apoſtles to ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and watchinge, &amp; we do gladly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thys was ſayd to al them that are godly. For ſith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the day of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde ſhall come as a thief, being vnknowen vnto al men, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame dredeful iudgement of Chriſt, before whoſe iudiciall ſeate, all men muſt apere, doth indifferently hang
<pb facs="tcp:13656:34"/> ouer al men, he doth well in the apoſtles warne, moniſh,<note place="margin">The libertins &amp; anabaptiſts do alege y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, by hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes.</note> &amp; exhort al men to watch Thou doſt bring the text of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euangelyſt vnperfit &amp; mutilate. For theſe be the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des. Watche ye therefore, for ye can not tel when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> houſe wil come, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther it wil be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euening, or at midnight or when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corkes crow, or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning leſt if he come ſodenly, he doth fynd you ſleping, That which I ſay to you, I doo ſay it to al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Thou canſt not deny, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> certain things are ſo ſet furth by Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in a maner, they perteine to al men, but not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a dyfference,<note place="margin">An apte and meet deuiſion of all thinges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded vs in the ſcriptures and word of god.</note> as when Chriſte ſaith: Ye are the ſalt of the earth. Ye are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of the world. For theſe things do ſo pertain to all them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> profeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane ſeaſon they do chiefly belong to the biſſhops, and theyr ſucceſſours: yea, &amp; to the magiſtrates. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayn, certayn thyngs are equally &amp; gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rally co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to al men: as he al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepts of mutual charitie &amp; loue, &amp; of forgi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their offences. Finally, certayne thynges are ſoo ſpoken, that they doo pertaine onely to the apoſtles, and to theyr ſucceſſours, the byſſhoppes and Paſtours, as: Goo ye throughoute
<pb facs="tcp:13656:35"/> al the world, and preache the goſpel to al creatures.<note place="margin">We ought not to make the perticuler precepts, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> Therfore, it is not lawfull too make the ſingulare preceptes, generall &amp; vniuerſall commaundementes. For he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reaſoneth on this maner: What ſoeuer is ſayd to the apoſtles, is ſayed to al men, it is ſayde to the apoſtlles, go intoo all the world, and preache: ergo, the ſame is ſaid to all men, doth reaſon foolyſhlye. For Paule ſayeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al be not apoſtles. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that, where he ſayeth. But ye ſhall not do ſo, is a perticulare or ſingular pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepte, &amp; perteyneth onely to the apoſtles and their ſucceſſours. Thou haſte not yet proued then, that a Chriſtian may not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the offyce of a magiſtrate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>By what argumentes, canſte thou thy ſelfe proue, that a Chriſtyan maye lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully execute the offyce of a magiſtrate?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>Of the election of the magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes we fynde wrytten in the .xviii.<note place="margin">Wold god al maieſtrates &amp; rulers, had al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>waies this place of the ſcripture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eien</note> chap. of Exodus, after this maner: Prouide or chooſe out of al people, wyſe men, which fear god, in whome the truth is, &amp; whych hate couetouſneſſe, and make of them, heades ouer the people &amp;c. I do ſuppoſe and thynke them, to be ryghtly choſen, which are choſen &amp; elected by them, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13656:35"/> it belongeth too,<note place="margin">How maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers be wel &amp; trewly choſen What ſhal we ſaie by them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by their office ſo dere, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be of neceſſitie compelled too ſpoile the kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ſubiectes for to make vp theyr monye agayne.</note> or whoſe parte it is to chooſe, electe, and make offycers, not, which do get offyces by fauor, by bribes or other deuyliſh waies and meanes; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (I ſaye) do I thinke to be lawfully cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, which either are ſuch as Iethro doth deſcribe here, or elles do ſtudye &amp; labour to be ſuche. I do ſuppoſe nowe, that it is ſufficiently proued, &amp; that by the wordes afore aleged, that ſuche godly men, may execute the office of a maieſtrate in god, for the words do ſignifie the ſame. They that are made rulers, muſt be iuſt, righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous, faythfull, trewe, fearing god, not co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uetouſe. But who can do theſe thynges better then a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? It foloweth agayn in the ſame chapiter. Yf thou doeſt theſe thinges, thou ſhalt fulfyl the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of god, &amp; ſhalt be able to ſuſteine or beare the commaundementes, or bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the lord. Sith then that a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to execute and do the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of god, which thynge is done by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mageſtrate, it foloweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a chriſtian may execute the office of a maieſtrate. Dothe not Paule ſaye that the mageſtrate, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſter of god? Romaines .xiii. chapter. Wherfore I do make mine argumente
<pb facs="tcp:13656:36"/> after this faſſhyon.<note place="margin">Marke and waie this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumente y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell Libertin.</note> All thynges wherby god is ſerued, are lawfull for a chriſtyan: but god is ſerued by a magiſtrate, ergo, it is not forbidden, that a Chriſtian ſhuld execute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offyce of a magyſtrate. Of this thing we haue innumerable examples of moſt holy men, which were magiſtrates as Abraham, Ioſeph, Iudas, Moiſes, Ioſue, Gedeon, Samuel, Dauid, Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as, Ioſias, and other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>What is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they did in the olde teſtament? If we may ſo gather oure argumente, it ſhal be proued by the ſame reaſon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt ſacrifice, &amp; offer vp bulles and goa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>Doth Paul pertain nothing to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>? That, which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> bringeſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacryfices hath no place here:<note place="margin">All ſacrifices are aboliſhed by Chriſte</note> Doſt thou not know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are aboliſſhed by Chriſte? But y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſt not proue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the magyſtrate is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſhed. Tel me now, I pray the, wer not Abraham, Moiſes, Samuel, &amp; the other, whome I haue recited, faithfull, and the frendes of god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>But they were not chriſtians.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>What is a chriſtian?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What a chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is.</note>Which beleueth in Chriſt Ieſus &amp; hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>Very well Tell me, had the apoſtles an other ſpirit then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophetes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>The ſpirite of
<pb facs="tcp:13656:36"/> the apoſtles, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of the prophets was al one.<note place="margin">The holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old Teſtamente were chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and alſo maieſtrates.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>The holy men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old teſtament, beleued in Chriſt, and had the ſpirit of Chriſte: ergo, they were chriſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and they were not onely chriſtyans but alſo magiſtrates, rulers, and officers then a chriſtian maye be a Magiſtrate. That the holy men of the old teſtament, had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of Chriſte, it is manifeſt by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt chap. of the .i. Epiſtle of Peter. For he ſpeaketh after this maner. Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſaluation. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophetes haue enquired &amp; ſought, which did prophecie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuld come vpon you, ſeking to whom or to what time, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of Chriſt, whych was in them, did ſignifie. And that they did beleue in Chriſt, Chriſt him ſelf doth teſtifie in the .viii. chap. of Ihon, &amp; Paul in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> .i. to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corin. &amp; .x. chap. They dyd all (ſpeaking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) eat one ſpirituall meat wyth vs, &amp; all did drinke one ſpiritual drinke. And they did drinke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpiritual rocke,<note place="margin">What diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is betwene the congregation of the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes &amp; our congregacion</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> folowed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; the rocke was Chriſt. The congregaty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> did beleue in thoſe day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, and of them that do beleue now, is al one, whiche congregation is gathered in one ſpirit. This difference onely there is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they did beleue in Chriſt, being promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb facs="tcp:13656:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> and which was yet to come, &amp; we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in him, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is alredy come &amp; exhibyted How they dyd eſteme, regarde, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the ceremonies, it is eaſye to be ſene in the prophets.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>Then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we do iudge, we muſt vſe the lawes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>That doth <add>not</add> folowe, ſyth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were no more bounde to the law, then we are. The marke that the chriſtian maieſtrate dothe ſhote at, is that peace &amp; iuſtice maye floriſhe, that men maye lyue righteouſly, godly, innocently, &amp; honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye: on the contrarie ſyde, that vyces and wickednes maie be roted out and puniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that ſedition, tumult, and rebellion and al ſuch other thinges, may be eyther taken hede of, or elles baniſhed awaie vt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terly. It ſcilleth not by what lawes theſe thynges be done, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they be done. We do not reade that the apoſtles dyd euer preache agaynſt the lawes of the genty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. And why? becauſe that the faſſhions lawes, and cuſtomes, of countreyes and natyons, were dyuerſe and ſundry, nor it could be poſſyble, that all thynges ſhuld be conuenyent for all menne. But what nede we to ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auncyent fathers? We wyll come to the newe teſtamente.
<pb facs="tcp:13656:37"/> Nicodemus, and Ioſeph dyd beare rule. He was the ſteward of Quene Candace that was baptized by Philip, &amp; receiued into the flocke of Chriſt Cornelius was a chriſtian, which dyd ſende for Peter, and was baptized by hym. Surgius Paulus and Eraſtus were receyued by Paule. Thou canſte not denye but that all theſe were common offycers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>They were officers, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they came to the faith but it is not expreſſedlye ſet forthe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they dyd remayne in theyr offyce, after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they dyd receiue the fayth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>Therfore I wyl heare by what reaſons thou canſt proue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faythe dyd put them from theyr office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>What neadeth any proba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, ſyth that it is not written, that they dyd abyde in theyr office?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Shewe then, that they dyd not continew in their office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>I can not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Then y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt proued nothing, &amp; myne arguments that I do bringe, are as ſtronge as thine. Trewly theſe queſtions do engender in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit contentions, &amp; bringe a mans mynd into perplexitie. Herken to me then.<note place="margin">The chriſtian fayth, doth put no man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys office.</note> The chriſtian faith, doth put no man from his empire, dominion, rule, or office: For Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeph and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other whiche we haue named
<pb facs="tcp:13656:38"/> before, were chriſtyans, &amp; were alſoo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike magiſtrats &amp; officers. Likewiſe, Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth not commaund y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouldiers to put a waie &amp; forſake warfare, inioyning the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhuld hurte or accuſe falſely no man, and that they ſhoulde be contente wyth theyr wages. Luke .iii. chapter. If faith, &amp; the name of a Chriſtian ſhuld con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrayne any man to goo from his power &amp; authority, truely it ſhuld compel him to go from the ſeruyce of god. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrate or officer, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſter or ſeruant of god. The Euangeliſte, when he maketh mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ioſeph of Arimathia, doth ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was a ſenator or alder man. Agayne he ſayth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was an honeſt &amp; iuſte man, but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out faith there can be no righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. (For by faith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteous doth liue) He is righteous, he is faithfull, he is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natour, ergo, a faythfull may be an alder man or ſenatour. Paul. Ro. xv. ſayth: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſtus y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> receyuer of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne, doth ſalute you. He was then in office, he was notte gone fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his office of a receiuer. For in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ii. to Tim. iiii. He did ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did dwel in Corinthus. Thou doſt not read y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Philip did forbid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eununchus his ſtewardſhip But now I wil hear whether thou canſt
<pb facs="tcp:13656:38"/> bring anye other thinge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>I haue no expreſſed wordes, touchyng the ſame But this doth ſeme vnto me moſt dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, &amp; moſt vnſemely for a chriſtyan, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould ſyt there, where many thinges are done againſt the law, &amp; againſt right as it is often times done in iudgementes and in the ſenate or parliamente houſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA.</speaker>
               <p>I haue proued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a chriſtan may execute the office of a Magiſtrate. What ſhall I ſay to thyne obiections? Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus &amp; Ioſeph were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloudy councel, where Chriſt was condemned, &amp; yet not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding, they were not polluted with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bloudy iudgement. For thei did not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> counſails of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly. Lu. xxiii Wherfore a chriſtian, is nothing harmed though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſate in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> councel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth not conſent to their filthy dedes &amp; actes, but defende &amp; counſayle, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is ryght, as much as lieth in him. Pſalme .i. But now loke vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinge more narowly, &amp; ponder it more diligent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, whether it is better y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> godly men and chriſtyans, ſhould be rulers and Magy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, or vngodlye perſons? For if the Magyſtrate be an infydell, what good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe can wee looke too haue of hym?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13656:39"/>
               <p>For he can do no maner of good him ſelf beinge not good, as be all they, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neyther know, nor worſhip god, which thinge ye do not deny your ſelues. Syth then that ye do ſay, that a chriſtian neither can, nor ought to beare rule or be a Magyſtrate, what other thynge do ye ſay, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ought to be no goodneſſe at al in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrate?<note place="margin">If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctryne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Libertins &amp; anabaptiſts ſhuld ſtand, al right &amp; iuſtice ſhuld be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted.</note> Which doctrine if it ſhould ſtand ſhuld not all ryght and iuſtice be peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? They that ay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a Chriſtian can not be a Magiſtrate, and graunt that the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly may, they ſeke nothing els, but to deſtroy al religyon and common weale. Can any man gouerne &amp; rule better then he that worſhpipeth god,<note place="margin">As kingdoms dyd alwayes floriſhe vnder godly &amp; vertu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous princes, ſo they haue ben ouerwhelmed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al kindes of calamites whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vngodly men did beare rule</note> and liueth inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cently before him? We do learne out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bokes of iudges, of Samuel, of Kynges, and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chronicles, that the Realmes &amp; kingdoms were neuer in a better &amp; more proſperous ſtate, then when godlye iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and kinges dyd beare rule. Againe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there were neuer ſo troublous tymes, ſo muche wyckednes, famine, hunger, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, tumultes, and calamytyes, as haue bene vnder vngodlye tyrauntes, as was Hieroboam, Achab, Manaſſes. &amp;c. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore we do now conclude, not onely that a chriſtian may execute the office of a ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrate,
<pb facs="tcp:13656:39"/> but alſo that ſuche an offyce can not be proſperouſly and wel adminiſtred but by chriſtians.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="dialogue">
            <head>¶ The ſecond Dialogue ¶ That the office of a magyſtrate, is not onely profytable, but alſo moſt neceſſary to a chriſtyan co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon weale.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>BVt what doſt thou ſay to this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt anſwereth to Pilate: My kyngdome is not of thys world? Sith then that chriſtyans are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med after Chriſt, ſurely (for ſoo it ſemeth to me) they ought to haue nothing to do with ſuche a kingdom, nor I thinke it to be neceſſary to the chyldren of god. For he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a true chriſtian, doth wronge and violence to no man, he doth not contend he doth not ſtriue, he hurteth no man, he ſmiteth no body, but liueth accordyng to the commaundemente of god. Math. v. chap.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſte was accuſed of high treaſon, agaynſte the imperiall Maieſty, wherby the Iues thought ſoone to haue condempned him. For they ſayd, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him ſelfe kynge of the Iewes Our lorde woulde be ſemed (as he oughte by ryght) to be ſo farre from the affectation
<pb facs="tcp:13656:40"/> and coueting of any earthly kingdome, that it ſhuld be agaynſt all reaſon, to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any ſuche thing of him. Therfore he did anſwere: My kingdom is not of this world, els I ſhould haue ſeruauntes and miniſters, which wolde endeuoure them ſelues, to defend me. So that Chriſt byd both confeſſe that he was king of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and alſo did ſignifie vnto Pilate, that he had no cauſe to be afraid of the kingdom that he did miniſter vnto, as thoughe he ſhould go about to chalenge it vnto him whereof the Iues did accuſe hym before Pilate.<note place="margin">The kingdom of Chriſte is not of thys world, but in ſpirit &amp; truthe</note> As though he ſhould ſay, I am a king, yet notwithſtanding, my kingdom is not of this world, but in ſpirit &amp; truthe</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI.</speaker>
               <p>This is my meaning. Then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom of Chriſte, is not of thys world, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, it doth not conſiſt in outward do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion &amp; power, wherby it foloweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is deſtituted or ſpoiled of glory, pomp, ri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches, &amp; outward puiſſaunce and myghte Wherfore we ought to be here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outcaſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, we ſhal at length reygne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> regeneration.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>I do ſaye nothing againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, but that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doſt gather therby, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtians haue no nede of a ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrate, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I do deny. The reaſon, why?
<pb facs="tcp:13656:40"/> Becauſe that Chriſte ſpeaketh ſo of hys kingdom, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mean ſeaſon,<note place="margin">Chriſt doth ſo ſpeake of hys kingdom, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mean ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he dothe not take awaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> politike magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrate.</note> he doth not condempne nor take away the magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrate. Beſides that, the chriſtians are not bare ſpirites, but they dwel yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh which they do cary about. As touchyng the ſpirit, by the whych man is renued &amp; made a chriſtian, he hath no nede of a ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrate. For the inwarde manne can be preſerued with no outward things. But as touching the fleſh, whiche he beareth about, &amp; his outward conuerſation, man hath as muche nede of a Magiſtrate, as of meat, and other outward things. For it is a lyke reaſon to ſay:<note place="margin">The Magy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is as ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſary to chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians in this worlde, as meat &amp; drinke</note> The kingdome of the chriſtians is not of this world, ergo they haue no nede of a magiſtrate, and to ſay: The kingdom of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtians, is not of this world: ergo, they nede no meate. For meat is eaten in this world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI.</speaker>
               <p>If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of a chriſtian man, is a true ſpiryt he hurteth no man. If he hurteth no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, what nedeth he a magyſtrate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Paul anſwereth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. Princes are not fear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful vnto them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do wel, but to them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do euil. Wilt thou not feare the power? Do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is good. and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt haue praiſe of it: for he is the miniſter of god, for thy good.
<pb facs="tcp:13656:41"/> Yf thou doeſt that thinge, which is euyll, feare, for he bereth not the ſwerd in vaine But he is the miniſter of god, to take pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhment &amp; vengeaunce of hym, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinge which is euill. Wherfore we muſt be ſubiects or obedient, not onely for fear of punyſhment, but alſo for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſake</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM,</speaker>
               <p>There ſhal be no nede of al theſe thinges: for the chriſtian knoweth, what Chriſt hath ſaied: Do not reſiſt or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>It is trew, a chriſtian ought not to reuenge him ſelfe raſhly, ſith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame doth perteine to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrate. But this doth beguile you,<note place="margin">The libertins and Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes do dreame that Chriſtians do not ſynne nor commyt any fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te.</note> that ye do ymagin &amp; dream, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the chriſtian people is ſuch, as it is not, nor euer was, nor euer ſhall be, yea ſuch, as it can not be: ye wyl, I ſay, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtians to be of ſuch a perfection, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man ſhal fall, or ſyn emong the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In thys ye are deceyued. For, although there be many good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtandyng there be many mo hipocrites. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old &amp; aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient partiarks, had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhuld hurte no man, they that were good in dede, &amp; godly, did wrong to no bodye, yet for the wycked ſake y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were emong them, there were, yea, them ſelfes were magiſtrates.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>Yf wee
<pb facs="tcp:13656:41"/> were trewe chriſtians, we ſhuld haue no nede of Magiſtrates.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>The old pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes were very godly men, &amp; yet not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding they had nede of a magiſtrate not for them ſelues, but for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked ſake We do not ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, yf we were ſuch,<note place="margin">If we had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, that we haue not, we wold do that, which we do not.</note> but of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are. Syth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we be not as we ought to be, it is neceſſary, that we haue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which, it is impoſſible for vs to liue. Yf we had great riches, truely we ſhuld be rich, if we had great lerning we ſhould w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out doubt, be great clearkes But we may not ſo gather, ergo, we nede not to labor, we nede not to ſtudy. Yf we had winges we ſhuld flee, ſith then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue no winges, we haue nede of fete to go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>We are al together vndone &amp; loſte. we are cleane caſt awaie, for we are no trew chriſtians.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe that we are yet ſoo vnperfite y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue nede of a magiſtrate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>Doſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not yet vnderſtande, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the magiſtrate is for the wicked ſake, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honeſty and vertue may be ſafe emong y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euyl perſons,<note place="margin">Why the Magiſtrate is ordeyned of God.</note> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god hath ordeyned it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>I do not vnderſtand, howe it hath bene ordeyned of god, ſyth that Chriſt ſayth: Do not ye reſiſt or withſtand euyll.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>He doth
<pb facs="tcp:13656:42"/> forbid that no priuate perſon,<note place="margin">No priuate perſon oughte to reuenge his wrong, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> belongeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrate.</note> ſhuld of af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection, reuenge his wronge, he doth not forbid, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a magiſtrate ſhuld not puniſſhe the euyl doers. For the power is the my<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſter of god, to puniſh &amp; take vengeance of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do committe euyl. Alſo, where Chriſt ſaith, when any man goeth about to take away thy cloke, giue him alſo thy rote, if thou doſt conferre it with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of Paul. i. Cor. vi. cha, thou ſhalt fynd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſaying, to be ſomewhat mollifyed, when he doth permit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhuld be iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gementes emong chriſtians, for thinges perteinyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſſe diligently y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of Paul, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt fynd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Paul permitteth no ſuch thing to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtians.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of Paul: Can any of you abide, hauing bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines, or to do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an other, too be iudged vnder vnryghtfull iudges, &amp; not rather vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſainctes? Do ye not know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaints ſhal iudge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world? And if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world be iudged by you, are ye vnworthye of ſmal iugements? Do ye not know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhal iudge angels, &amp; not only thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pertain to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuing? Therfore yf ye haue iudgements, touching thoſe things y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pertain to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of life, make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are vileſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I do ſpeake to your ſhame.
<pb facs="tcp:13656:42"/> Is there not emong you a wyſe man? not as muche as one? whych can geue iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment betwene brother and brother? But one brother ſtriueth with an other, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnder infidels. Therfore nowe there is a great fault in you, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye haue ſtrife emong you.<note place="margin">The place of Paul is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed.</note> Why do not ye rather ſuffer wrong Whye do ye not receiue harme? yea, but rather ye do iniury and wronge, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to your brethren. Theſe, I ſay, be the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Paul, wherbye we do learne, that we ought rather to ſuffer wrong, and to receiue paciently harme, then to ſtryue &amp; contende emong our ſelues, wheruntoo Chriſt, in the .vi. of Mathewe, hath a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte. But if thys, for the imbecyllytye, weakenes, and corruption of our fleſſhe, can not be done, there be Magyſtrates, courtes, and iudges, before whom, ſuche matters, if any do chaunce, may be diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed and pacifyed, too the intents, that he, which ſuffreth wrong, may be reuenged and he that doth the wrong, may be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſhed and holden in.<note place="margin">Wherefore courtes and iudges ſerue, looke vpon thys, O ye iudges.</note> Now they that ſo contend before a iudge, for thynges that pertayne to the vſe of lyfe, are chriſtians for Paul ſaith: One brother doth wrong to an other, whom he commaundeth (yf
<pb facs="tcp:13656:43"/> nede do ſo require) to ſue for their righte before chriſtian iudges. For brothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and chriſtian, are al one. Finally, by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd wordes, it may be manifeſtly gathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, that a chriſtian may execute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offyce of a magiſtrate.<note place="margin">Saynctes are euerye where in the ſcriptur taken for the faythfull.</note> For he apointed the ſain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes to be iudges, and here the ſainctes be put for the faithfull whom he wil rather to be choſen of the vileſt ſorte in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, then that they ſhould repayre to vnfaithfull iudges.</p>
               <p>Of all theſe thinges we do gather and conclude that the faithfull haue nede of a magiſtrate, ſith that the congregation is gathered of good and euyll, the faithfull them ſelues being in the fleſh, as long as they liue. And again, ſith that the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes and elect of god, had nede of a ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrate: We haue no leſſe nede then thei had. Therfore the magiſtrate is not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly profitable, but alſo moſt neceſſary to a chriſtian common weale.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="dialogue">
            <head>¶ The third Dialogue. That we are bound to obey the Magiſtrate.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>THoſe thyngs that thou haſt brought oute of Paule, doo
<pb facs="tcp:13656:43"/> pleaſe me very wel, but I do not ſe, that we are bound to obey thys Magiſtrate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI</speaker>
               <p>What is this? Doſte thou thinke that we are not bounde to obey y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power which is of god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>I would not be greatly againſt it, if al power wer of god if they did al rule wel, if they dyd defend right &amp; equitie. What if this power doth fighte againſt god, doth breake &amp; violate lawes and ſtatutes, doth oppreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poor wylt thou ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is of god? or doſt thou thinke that we are bound to obey it? As farre as I can iudge, a tyrannical power is not of God, yea, rather it is no power ergo, we oughte not to obey it.<note place="margin">The tiranous poweris geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, as a rod to punyſh and try the people.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DA.</speaker>
               <p>A tyrannouſe power is alſo of god, gyuen of god, as a rodde wherewith the people is bothe tryed and punyſſhed.</p>
               <p>Whych thyng is made moſt playne and manyfeſt in Pharao, in Saule, and Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaſar. Paule alſo doth ſaye, that all po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMON.</speaker>
               <p>Paule ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of that power, which is benefycyall to the good, and punyſſheth the wycked But contrarye to that, a tyraunte dothe wronge to them that are good and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, he oppreſſeth them, and dothe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunce and ſet vp the wycked. Sith then
<pb facs="tcp:13656:44"/> that ſuche power is not beneficyall to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good,<note place="margin">God doth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ſemeth euyll to vs, for the good of the electes.</note> but rather do them wronge, howe can it be of god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>That thing whych ſemeth euyl vnto vs, god doth ordeyn it to the good of his elect. Did not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe &amp; death of ſo many martyrs, which were ſlaine and put to death by tyrauntes and cruel perſecutours, ſerue to the glorye of god, and to the increaſe of their own fely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>citie and beatitude?<note place="margin">That officers and rulers do ſometymes waxe tyrants it cometh ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the vy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in offyce or els, of the Ire &amp; wrath of God.</note> God vſeth Nabugo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donoſor as a rodde, wherwith he punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth his people. Beſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, if any chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges and alterations do happen, ſo that he which was a good magyſtrate, a godlye ruler &amp; officer, is cleane chaunged, &amp; doth become moſt wicked, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> procedeth not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of the magiſtrate, or office, but it commeth of the vices of moſt peruerſe &amp; wicked men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in office, &amp; execute the office of a magiſtrate, yea, many and ſun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dry times it commeth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plain yre and wrath of god. Are not many times y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter &amp; ayre, yea, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meat it ſelfe peſtiferous which notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding by them ſelues, are moſt wholſom. But ſo god doth puniſh our ſinnes. Vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tiran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nous magiſtrates.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI.</speaker>
               <p>What if he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth that, whyche is vniuſte and vnryghtfull? Shall I obey?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13656:44"/>
               <p>What yf the tyraunt be both vnryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and vngodly, ſhall I obey neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les? No. For thou haſt ſayd before, that no man can better execute the office of a magiſtrate, then a chriſtian. Again, Paul doth with a certaine ſtomacke, ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them that ſuffered them ſelues to be iudged vnder vnryghtuous iudges. Finally, the apoſtles them ſelues, wold not obey the commaundementes of the vngodlye magiſtrates, ſaying: It beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth rather to obey god, then men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>I haue made a compariſon betwixte the godly magiſtrate, and the vngodly, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſaid theſe wordes: No man can better nor more godly execute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, then a godly man,<note place="margin">Thoughe the vngodlye ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrate is not to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtandynge in externe &amp; out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward thyngs hee is not to be diſobeyed.</note> and yet in the meane ſeaſon, I did not ſay, that an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and tirannous magyſtrate, is not a magiſtrate. I did preferre the rule that the chriſtian doth beare, before the rule y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vngodly doth beare, &amp; yet notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, I did not condempne the laſte although it were no power, or rule, or as though we were not bounde to obey it. The commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weales neuer floriſſhed bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, then when godly men did Raygne. That we may ſe in Ezechias, &amp; other ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:13656:45"/> Kinges. Wherunto ſame Paul had al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo a reſpecte when he did bid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to choſe &amp; make iudges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaints, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfull. The apoſtles dyd wel, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in certain things they did not obey y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly edictes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſenate. When y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doſt then aſke and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, touchyng obedience, I do aunſwere after thys maner: When y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſaieſt theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Too obey an vngodly magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrate, &amp; to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey vngodlye lawes &amp; ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, is not all one.</note> Shall I obey an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly magiſtrate? Shal I obey vngodly lawes, ſtatutes and commaundementes? Thou doſt not aſke all one thynge. Thy queſtion &amp; demaund is not al one. For to the firſt queſtion, I do anſwere y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are bound to obey, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond again I ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ought not to obey. The magiſtrate be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth no rule ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules, but ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies &amp; outward ſubſtance, &amp; whatſoeuer doth perteyn to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward conuerſation of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now if he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth any thing againſt god, againſt conſcyence &amp; health of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, we ought rather to obey god, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of the tirant. Now hath place y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the apoſtes do ſay: It behoueth rather to obey god, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men. But if he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth only y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che perteineth to outward thinges, or to
<pb facs="tcp:13656:45"/> thy body, which thing, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                     <p>We owgh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to a tyrant, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, we owe no obedience, that is to ſaie, in outwarde thynges we owe to obey, but in matter of conſcience yf he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth any thynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte god we are not bound to obey Why the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrate doth medle in mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters of relygyon.</p>
                     <p>What profyt doth come of the ſtatutes and ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of godly magiſtrates.</p>
                  </note> or may be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fourmed &amp; done by the, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the loſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth &amp; righteouſnes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out paril of ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation (though it ſemeth neuer ſo hurtful to thy body and ſubſtaunce, though it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth neuer ſo vncomely for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>) thou arte bound to obey. Therfore we owe obedy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence to the tirant, &amp; againe, we owe hym not obedience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI.</speaker>
               <p>Now an other queſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on doth riſe, Yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publike magiſtrate bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth no rule ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, why doth then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrat now a daies, vſurpe ſo much power, in matters of faith?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>He doth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, not as a magiſtrate only, but as a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian magiſtrate, nor he doth it, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement &amp; example. In Deutero. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng is commaunded to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law by him, &amp; to read it dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly which boke alſo is delyuered to Ioſue by Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Let vs loke vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> example of Ioſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ada, Ioſias, Ezechias, Nabugo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>donozer &amp; Darius in Daniel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI.</speaker>
               <p>Haue they any power ouer the ſoule &amp; ſpirit of man, or can they print faith by their ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, in the heartes of men?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO</speaker>
               <p>No forſothe: But their ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; ordinaunces do profit in this thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vngodly do leſſe harme, do commit
<pb facs="tcp:13656:46"/> leſſe offence, leſſe ydolatry &amp; blaſphemy being fraied, cohibited &amp; brideled by ſuch godly edictes &amp; proclamatyons. Els the weake, by ſuch licencious doings of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly, eyther are letted to come to Chriſt or elles too take occaſyon, too ſwerne a waie from Chriſt, &amp; his worde. Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is done by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laws of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrats, doth bring this to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is leſſe euil &amp; harme emong mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men, that men do lyue godly, honeſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, &amp; quietly, and although, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly do hide their vngodlynes, malice and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes within in their heartes, yet not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtanding they dare not ſuffer it to breake forth, to trouble diſquiet, &amp; offend them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will liue godly. God onely doth loke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearte, &amp; iudgeth it. Wherefore I thinke this propoſition, to be ſufficiently proued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are bound to obey the Magiſtrate For, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrate be a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo much more ought we to obey hym. Againe, yf he be an heathen and vngodly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> art al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo bound to obey him though he dothe oppreſſe the, in thy body and ſubſtaunce ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth not call y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god &amp; the truth But let vs make it ſtronger w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs, In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xx. of Luk, Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth
<pb facs="tcp:13656:46"/> to giue to Ceſar, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whych belongeth too Ceſar, &amp; to god,<note place="margin">What by Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar we owe to vnderſtand in the ſcriptures</note> that which belongeth to god. By Ceſar he vnderſtandeth general<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maieſtrats of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our bodies &amp; goodes are ſubiects .i. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, viii. Our mynd doth only belong to god, &amp; therfore touchyng it, we are more bound to obey god, then man. Peter tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth vs after this maner: Be ye ſubiect to al humain ordynaunce for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord ſake, whether it be to a king, as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent, or to his deputes, which are ſence of him, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puniſhment of the euil doers, &amp; to the praiſe of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do wel, for ſo is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil of god, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by wel doing, ye ſtop y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thes of ignorant perſons. &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI.</speaker>
               <p>Ye haue alwaies taught out of Eſaias, &amp; wordes of Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god is worſhipped in vain, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> precepts &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements of men, &amp; now ye affirme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plain contrary oute of Peter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are bound to obei al humain ordinaunces.<note place="margin">Ther be two kyndes of hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>main traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>Humayne traditions or conſtitutions, are taken .ii. waies. Some are ſet furth too this ende, that they ſhuld be a worſhipping of god which men do preſcribe vntoo other, as neceſſarye to ſaluation, whych yf a man ſhoulde omytte and neglecte, he ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:13656:47"/> greuouſly ſinne &amp; offend: again, if he ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth them, they thinke them ſelues, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo make other too beleue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he deſerueth much of god. With theſe preceptes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, which are mere inuenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of men, god is worſhipped in vayn. There are again certain conſtitutions of magiſtrats, touching heritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, proprie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, ſelling and bying, letting furth tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching publike contractes &amp; ſuche lyke, of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which things, princes &amp; magiſtrats do make lawes &amp; conſtitutyons, for a peace &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon quietnes &amp; tranquilitie. Al men generally are bound to obey al ſuche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions &amp; lawes. And of ſuche Peter doth ſpeake, as it appereth manifeſtly by his words. Beſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, Peter writeth not to the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to the chriſtians, which were diſperſed here &amp; there .i. Pet. ii. cha To Titus .iii. chap. it is writen after this maner. Warne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſayth ſaint Paule) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be ſubiect to Princes &amp; poteſtates, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they be obedient too magiſtrates &amp; ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be ready to al good works, &amp; that they ſpeake euyl of no man. To the Roma. xiii. he ſayth. Euery ſoule (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, all men &amp; women) be ſubiects to the higher powers, for ther is no power but
<pb facs="tcp:13656:47"/> of god: &amp; al the powers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are, be ordened of god. Therfore, whoſoeuer doth reſyſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power, doth reſiſt the ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god But they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reſiſt, ſhal receiue to them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues dampnation.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="dialogue">
            <head>The fourth Dialogue. ¶ Whether it be lawful to reſiſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrate, where we do write a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them that do rebel againſt magiſtrates &amp; rulers.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
               <p>Tel Ioiada, if there were a magiſtrat (as ther be to mani) which ſhuld do nothing wel, nothing ſoberly, nothing iuſtly, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cording to right, which being rebellyous to god, &amp; his lawes, ſhuld w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> infynit wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, oppreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good, &amp; not reuenge them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuffer wrong, nor yet delyuer them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the handes of their enemyes, were it not lawful to reſiſt him? Doth not Eſaias cal the wicked maieſtrats theues &amp; robbers? Eſai. i. Doth not Chriſt cal them the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of darkenes? Paul doth reuile Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias to his face. Actes. xxiii. calling hym a whited or painted wall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>To an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly &amp; wicked magiſtrate, his faultes &amp; wicked dedes are to be ſhewed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may turne from them, to a better life, and that
<pb facs="tcp:13656:48"/> ought to be done now in time, now out of time. The fact of Paul hath ſome occaſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on. Be thou lyke to Paul, and then imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate and folow Paules dede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIMO.</speaker>
               <p>What auaileth if the wicked dedes of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrates and prynces be rebuked, ſythe that they be wicked ſtil, and amand not? It were farre better that they ſhould be roted out of the earth, euen as Iehu, and other did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>Why, and wherfore doſt thou ſay ſo my Symon? How farre haſt thou ouer ſhoot thy ſelf? do not ye Cata<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baptiſtes dateſt and abhorre warrely tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multes? But I ſe what it would be, if al thinges ſhould happen and chaunce too you,<note place="margin">All y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doyngs of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts do breath and ſauour tu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mult &amp; confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all thynges.</note> accordyng to your owne deſires, I feare me, leſt all your doings do breathe and ſauour tumulte and confuſyon of all thynges, Not ſo, my Simon. Paul ſaith i. Cor. vii. chapter. Let euery man abyde in that vocation that he is called in. Arte thou called, being a ſeruaunt? Care thou not therfore, but alſo, if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſte be made free, vſe rather the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>Thou doſt heare then, that he doth preferre fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and libertie, to ſeruitude &amp; bondage and warneth that (if it may be done) we do ſeke it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>I heare that fredom and
<pb facs="tcp:13656:48"/> libertie is to be wiſſhed for, and alſo (yf it may be done conueniently) to be embra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced, but I do not heare,<note place="margin">Liberti ought not to be ſought by ſedition and bloud ſheding If all thinges were done, as we would, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery houre tumultes ſhoulde ryſe.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it oughte to be deſired &amp; ſought, by ſeditions, by tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, by euyl waies, by violence, bloude, &amp; warres. Nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles did euer vſe ſuch meanes, for to be made free, or to get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to libertie, therefore we muſte ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne alſo from them. If al things were done by our councell, euery houre tumul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and ſeditions, ſhould be ſtyrred vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the magiſtrate, for euerye man (as ſoone as any thing ſhould not come too paſſe, according to his luſte, &amp; inordynate deſire) ſhuld begin an vprore &amp; tumulte, &amp; wold ſay: The magiſtrate is vngodly, he hath handled me agenſt al right &amp; equity Shoulde not thus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtyan name be a cloke of tumults, inordinate affections,<note place="margin">The Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins go about to make the Chrſtian name, a cloke of tumultes &amp; confuſion.</note> &amp; of al confuſion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI.</speaker>
               <p>Truly thys thynge muſt be tried &amp; proued by hands, and by ſtrength, for wordes do not auaile wyth thoſe tirauntes. By and by, as ſoone as anye manne doth rebuke their tirannye, and wycked factes,<note place="margin">O brayneles Anabaptiſte</note> they waxe hote and angrye, they threaten, they take, they caſte intoo pryſon, they ſpoyle menne of their goodes, they baniſhe, they kyll and
<pb facs="tcp:13656:49"/> murther the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are godly. This waie ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther godlynes, nor iuſtice, nor good men are ſene to. Therfore this ſore ſickenes &amp; diſeaſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale, can not be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, but by tumult &amp; the ſwerd, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly may be vtterly deſtroyed, &amp; roted out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IO.</speaker>
               <p>That thing which to men ſemeth impoſſible, before god is poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible. Therfore, this high &amp; waighty vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines, &amp; matter, ought to be committed to god, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt erneſt &amp; burning praiers, for he ſaith:<note place="margin">God dothe neuer forſake hys electe.</note> Put or remyt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gaunce to me &amp; I wil reueng or require. It is moſt ſure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god doth neuer forſake, his electe, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth neuer deny hys helpe vnto them that with a ſincere heart, and trew faith do call vpon him.<note place="margin">To them that are godly, all thyngs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god doth, ſeme well done.</note> Luk. xviii.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>But he doth helpe manye to late.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>To them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are godly in dede, nothinge doth ſeme to ſoone, nothinge to late, that the lorde god doth worke. They do receyue with a thankful heart, what ſo euer their merciful father doth geue, whether it be weale or woo, they knowe that they are alwaies in the handes of their moſt bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous father from the whiche, nothynge can take them awaie. They do commyt them ſelues altogether, to this moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifull
<pb facs="tcp:13656:49"/> father, yelding them ſelues whollye to his will. For, they do remember y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of Peter, which ſaith. The lord kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth how to deliuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly from temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation, &amp; how to kepe the vnrighteous to be puniſhed in the day of iudgement.<note place="margin">Marke theſe golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayings and prynte them in thy mynd, who ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer thou be, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> art opreſſed and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting thy ſelf holly into the mercy of thyne heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of deuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyſhe tumult &amp; inſurrection</note> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that ſaying of Dauid ſtycked in theyr mindes: I neuer ſawe the righteous for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Finally y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> golden ſentence of Paul is neuer from their memory: God ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not vs to be tempted aboue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we be able, to beare, &amp; maketh a ioyful &amp; proſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rous ende wyth the temptation. Wyth out doubt god doth alwaies deliuer hys trew ſeruauntes, for eyther he doth illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate and lighten the heartes of the ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunts &amp; princes, that they ſhall fauoure his electe, as he dyd to Pharao, towarde Ioſeph, too Cirus, toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, to Xerxes, toward Eſeras, to Artaxerxes, to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde Rehemiah, to Ahaſuerus, toward Mardorche, to Nabugodonozer, toward Daniel, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful and godly might haue ſome reſpit. Or yf he be determined to vtterly deſtroye the tyrantes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly rulers, he begynneth that matter with ſo great, and ſo notable ſignes and tokens, that no man canne doubt of the
<pb facs="tcp:13656:50"/> good wyll of God, and alſoo he doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes atcheue and fynyſh the thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath begon, wyth a proſperous ende Now yf any man doth go about any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyueraunce,<note place="margin">
                     <p>Note thys dreadful ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael, whyche killing Godo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly as, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Baby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lonians de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, dyd bring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunt of the Iſraelites to vtter confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon.</p>
                     <p>All ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are oppreſſed let neuer thys goodly hyſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry be from your hert, and then I truſte that ye ſhall neuer haue mynd to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection &amp; tumult, but rather to call erneſtley vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god for dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance.</p>
                  </note> wythoute, or agaynſte thys order, as thoughe he had begonne or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpryſed that thyng, by the wyll and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundemente of God, he ſhall auayl no more then Iſmael dyd agaynſt the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biloniens, in kyllyng Godolias .iiii. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kynges .xxv. chapter. and Hieremye .xl. chapter. But go to, we wyl bryng furth out of the armorye and ſtorehouſe of the ſcryptures, weyghtye exaumples, where by it ſhall be made manyfeſte and plaine bothe by what meanes, god delyuereth hys electe, and alſoo howe vnfortunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and vnluckelye, they dyd ſpede, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che dyd go aboute to delyuer theym ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues by boldenes ond tumulte agaynſte the wyll of God. The people of Iſrael dydde ſerue in Egipte, certayne hundred yeares, beynge oppreſſed wyth ſundrye and dyuers labours, and greuouſlye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flycted, beſydes that, they were compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led too ſe howe theyr chyldren and infan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, as ſoone as they were borne, were drowned in the ryuer of Nilus. By and
<pb facs="tcp:13656:50"/> by, as ſoone as they beganne too call to the Lorde wyth a trewe heart, they were hearde of the Lorde. For he dydde ſende Moiſes, whyche ſhoulde be a captayne and a delyuerer of the people. He dydde carye theym drye ſhoed thoroughe the redde Sea, and dydde drowne Pharao, wyth all hys hoſte and armye, in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the deepe. Exodus the fourtene Chapter. Saule, kynge of the Iſraelites, dyd kyll and murther the Prophetes of God, and perſecuted the innocente and ryghtuouſe Dauid.<note place="margin">Oh moſt god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Dauid, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might haue grace in our troubles and affections and when we are moſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue &amp; folowe thy ſteppes, god graunte, we maye.</note> Dauid dothe notte reuenge hym ſelfe, nor put hym from hys kyngdome, but rather he flyeth him ſelfe, and when he had fallen twyſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too hys handes, he ſpare hym, and dyd ſuffer hym too goo awaye vnhurte, or wythoute harme, ſayinge: The Lorde be mercyfull vntoo mee, that I doo not that thynge too my Lorde, the anoynted of the Lord, that I ſhould lay mine hand vpon him, for he is the anointed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord The Lorde lyueth, that excepte, the lorde doth ſmyte hym, or hys daye become that he dye, or he, goyng downe too bat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayle, do peryſſhe, the lorde be mercyfull
<pb facs="tcp:13656:51"/> vnto me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I do not lay mine hand vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> anointed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord .i. of the kings xxiiij. At an other tyme, when Abiſai did ſaye. The lord hath ſhutte vp to day thine ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>my into thine hands, now therfore wil I thruſt him thorow w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſpear to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground once, &amp; it ſhall be no nede of the ſeconde time. Dauid ſayde vnto Abiſai: Doo not ſley him. For who ſhal lay his hands vp on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> anointed of the lord, &amp; ſhall be vngil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie? .i. of the kinges .xxvi. cha. Theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, my Simon, being wel weighed and pondered, do teach vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt not fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blynd affection of our fleſſhe. For when the time was come y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lorde had appointed, not Dauid, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord him ſelf did take Saul away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſwerd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he him ſelf had ſent, &amp; dyd ſet vp Dauid in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roial &amp; kingly ſeat. The chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, haue bene many times af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flicted vnder tirants &amp; vngodly kynges, as we haue in the hiſtory of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudges, no man did go about of his own head, or of his owne induſtry, to deliuer them. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord him ſelf did deliuer them by Gede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, Samſon, Iephte, &amp; other like, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he him ſelfe had choſen to ſuche buſineſſes. Who doth by ſedition &amp; tumult, inuade
<pb facs="tcp:13656:51"/> or come vpon the vngodly king Achab. when he doth ſet vp ydols, &amp; commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> innocent &amp; good man, Naboth, to be ſtoned to death, keping neither ryght nor equitie, ſlaying the prophetes, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Helias (tyl y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord doth ſtyrre vp Eliſeus, which at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commaundement of god doth anoint Iehu king, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhuld take vengeaunce for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, of the vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly .iiii. of the kinges .ix.x. So Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ada did vnto Athalia, ſo the king of the Aſſirians did to Manaſſes. How long time did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperours of Rome, ſhede the chriſtian bloud, yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtandyng no man goeth about to better it by tumult, til Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinus Magnus did come. I could reherſe vnto the Thraſibulus, a tirant of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienſes, &amp; William Tell, &amp; Stouffaker, ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rants of the Heluetians, but we wyll be content w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the examples of the ſcripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI.</speaker>
               <p>Shalt it then be alwaies lawful to ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rants to be vngodly, &amp; that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment? which of the words of Paul. Ro. xiii. Do take a cloke, a buckeler &amp; ſhielde of their own malice, vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they fraude &amp; deceiue, they ſteale, they robbe, they ſlaye, they murther, &amp; confounde all things, they euery foote ſlea y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poor com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons
<pb facs="tcp:13656:52"/> to the very bones, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> new exacty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, taxes, &amp; ſubſidies, being in the mean ſeaſon, giuen to riot, and outragyous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, to drunkennes, to vnlawful gaining to whordome, and moſt vniuſte warres, and therwith committing moſte deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dedes, and wycked factes agaynſte god, and the common weale. But I wil ſhewe to the out of Hieremy .xv. chap, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the people is puniſſhed of god, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they thus ſuffer tyrauntes and vngodly prynces, to kyll and flea, without any pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhment. For after the .iiij. plagues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth rehearſe there, he addeth by and by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe, ſaying: And I wil deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp into the fury of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the earthe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay: I wil ſtyrre vp againſte them the fury &amp; rage of al the kingdoms of the earth, for Manaſſes ſake, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of Eze<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chias, the kyng of Iuda, for all the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath done at Ieruſalem. Se in the .vii. of the kynges .xxi. chapt, what wyckednes he did commit, if the Iewes had not ſuffered their kynge, thus w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out puniſhment, to be ſo wycked, they ſhuld not haue bene ſo greuouſlye plagued of god. It behoueth to pull oute the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding eie, &amp; to caſt it away, likewiſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:13656:52"/> hand and of the fote,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Here be .ij. queſtions. The firſte is: whether the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunte muſt be remoued from his roume or not? The ſeconde: howe, and by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Therfore I do not deny, but that a wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked magyſtrate, muſt be put downe, but not the ſame way that thou wylte. Noo man ought to kyll hym, nor to ſtyrre vp warre and ſedition againſt him, we muſt go to worke, an other maner of way, the matter muſte be attempted and aſſayed by lawful meanes, for god hath called vs in peace .i. Corinthians the ſeuenth chap the tyraunt muſt be taken away (that do I not denye) for Samuel dothe depoſe Saule from hys offyce, and doth anoynt Dauid, kynge ouer the people of Iſrael. Ioiada putteth furthe Athalia from the ruledome and maketh Ioas a kynge. If then a kynge be made by the common aſſente of all the people, and begynneth too be wycked, let hym agayne be put downe wyth common aſſente of the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, excepte they wyll all be punyſſhed wyth hym. And yf he be choſen by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent &amp; election of fewe princes, let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſignifie &amp; ſhew unto them, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wycked
<pb facs="tcp:13656:53"/> and vngodly lyfe of thys kinge, &amp; that it ought to be borne or ſuffered no longer, let them be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, that haue choſen him, to put him doune agayn. Now here ſhall be all the labour,<note place="margin">What the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt wyll do to them, that dare ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked tirannye.</note> for againſt them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> do thys thyng, the tyraunt ſhall exercyſe all kynde of crudelytye, handlyng them accordynge to hys inordynate luſte, and whome it ſhall pleaſe hym, he wyll ſleye and murther. But it is a gloryous thing to dye for ryghtuouſnes, and the truth of God. And better it is too be ſlayne, for the defence of iuſtyce and ryghtuouſnes then aſſentyng vnto vnryghtuouſnes,<note place="margin">It is far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be put to death for defence of righteouſnes, then after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes to be kylled, wyth the vngodly and wycked. What we owe to do yf he be come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngdome by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwerde, or by enhery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce.</note> or dyſſembling, to be afterwardes kylled to the vngodly and wicked. They that can not awaye wyth thys thynge, let theym ſuffer and beare a vycyous and proude tirannie, and wyth hym, let theym loke too receyue an extreame punyſſhemente Yet notwythſtandyng, the hande of the lorde is ſtretched furthe, and threateneth a plague. Finally, yf he hath inuaded or come into the kyngdome, by anye other chaunce, as by ſtrengthe, or by enhery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, we muſte beare hym, till the lord vouchſafe to delyuer the oppreſſed, leſte any commotyon and tumulte be ſtyrred
<pb facs="tcp:13656:53"/> vp by vs, for the kingdom of god is righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuouſnes, peace, and gladnes in the holy ghoſt. Romay .xiiii. There be then many waies, wherby tiraunts may be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and put downe, but we do wante a feruent ſtudy of rightuouſnes, and of the truth, we do wante the feare of god, and deuiliſh wickednes reigneth eueri where For it could not be poſſible that a tirant durſt do ſo muche, except there were mo wycked, by whom he ſhould mainteyne and vphold his tyrannye. But fyrſt and formeſt, the prophetes, that is to ſay, the miniſters of gods word, muſt be bold to rebuke the ſynnes and wycked factes of Prynces &amp; rulers:<note place="margin">Which is the moſt commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious way, to ouercome ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauntes.</note> none other way more commodious to ouercome tirauntes can be, then if the preachers of the truthe, do once determyne too dye, they muſte put their bodies &amp; lyues to ieopardy. Yf Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, Dominitanus, Maximianus, wyth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, could not by murtheringe and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of bloud, roote out and vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye the doctrine of Chriſt, muche leſſe ſhall theſe braynleſſe and madde princes (yf we do ſtand vp boldly) oppreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pel and the truth.<note place="margin">This is not ſpoken in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye godlye prince, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Therfore this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt and chiefeſt way, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ouerſeers be not
<pb facs="tcp:13656:54"/> blynde, that the dogges be not dombe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they put them ſelues a wall betwixte the ſynnes of the people, and god, that they amend vp the broken hedge. The ſecond that we do always,<note place="margin">The lawfull wayes and meanes to get our ſelues out of myſerable oppreſſyon.</note> and without ceaſſing praye vnto god, whych in his wrath and indignation, maketh the hypocrytes too reigne, for our ſinnes. Finally, and laſt of all, that we thyrſt for ryghteouſnes, that we amend our liues, and chaunge our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dytyons. For yf we be godly, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, it is impoſſible, that a tyraunte do reigne longe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>All Iſrael, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Salomon, did ſwarue awaye, &amp; forſake Roboam, becauſe he oppreſſed them to muche, &amp; that of their own head iii. of the kynges, and .xiii. chapter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Why, doeſt thou not reade, that, whiche foloweth:<note place="margin">Why Gobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am dyd not graunt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, wherfore he was vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forſaken of ten trybes.</note> And the kinge did not graunt the people their petytyon, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hath forſaken hym, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might, or ſhould perfourme hys word, that he had ſpoken in the handes of Achias the Silonite, to Hieroboam, the ſonne of Nabate. Thou canſt not proue by this, that it is lawfull for any man to make inſurrection of hys own head, agaynſt tyrants, or euil rulers</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>I feare, leaſt thys doctrine wyll
<pb facs="tcp:13656:54"/> make men ſluggiſh, negligent, &amp; daſtards that if at any time, the lorde doth ſende a deliuerer, they wyl be in doubt, of the wil of the lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Care for other thyngs when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord doth begin and go about ſo hygh things, he calleth not ſluggyſhe da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtards, and negligent perſons:<note place="margin">Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god wil put doune ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauntes, he doth alwayes ſtyrre vp men meete for the purpoſe.</note> he geueth wiſdom, confidence &amp; boldnes, he giueth luſtynes of courage, and ſtrength, &amp; brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth all thinges to the appoynted ende. Which thing we may ſe in Moiſes, Ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deon, and other. The godly man, doth di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>recte al thynges to peace, vnitie, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cord. Again, he knoweth that the people is puniſhed, if prynces do rule &amp; gouerne wickedly.<note place="margin">The ſolicitud and care of a godly man.</note> Theſe things do make a godly and faithful man, heauy, &amp; ful of thought and kyndell him with a certain ſtudye of godlynes, theſe thinges do make him to beware, and circumſpect, not temerouſe raſh, and ouer bold, theſe thinges do con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtraine him to pray earneſtly to god, and to thinke both day and nighte, vpon the amendement and redreſſe of thoſe things that are done and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted againſt god. Then god doth open the waies, wherby the deſyres of the godly may be fulfilled nor doth forſake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that put their truſte
<pb facs="tcp:13656:55"/> and confidence in hym, nor yet dothe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe or put them backe, that cry and cal vpon him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>When the tyraunt ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth, that he maye do al thinges, without puniſhment, he euery day waxeth worſe, and more hygh minded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>What ſo euer he ſeeth, let hym be ſure, that an vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſtruction doth hang ouer him,<note place="margin">Who ſoeuer doth miſuſe the longe ſuffraunce of god, ſhall not eſcape puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment.</note> if he wyl continue ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yl in his wickednes. For no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did euer eſcape w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out puniſhment that dyd miſuſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> long ſuffraunce of god</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI.</speaker>
               <p>Why doo ye then euery where de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>predicate and ſay, that they are like vnto Iudas the Gaulonite, and not chriſtians that wil not obey the magiſtrates and ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers?<note place="margin">No godly man doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſte the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe that no godly man doth reſiſt the magiſtrate. For ſith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the apoſtles do warne &amp; byd vs to obey hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thenyſh magyſtrates, who doth not ſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is an vnfittely thyng for a chriſtian, to ſhew him ſelfe diſobedient to a chriſtyan magiſtrate?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>That were wel ſayd yf we had a chriſtyan Magiſtrate.<note place="margin">Who is to be called a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyan magy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI</speaker>
               <p>I do cal him a chriſtian magiſtrate, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is baptyzed in Chriſte Ieſus, which beleueth in Chriſt, doth confeſſe him, and heareth hys goſpell, which he dothe alſo ſuffer to be preached emong his ſubiects
<pb facs="tcp:13656:55"/> nor doth perſecute it, withſtandynge (as muche as in him lyeth) wickedneſſe and iniquitie, or vnryghteouſnes and punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the euil doers, that do offend open<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, which doth bend al his care and ſtudy to this, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of god may increaſe, may be promoted and ſet forth, that men maye lyue godly, honeſtly, and quyetly in the common weale. And (thankes be giuen to god) we do not want ſuch now a daies, emong the magiſtrates and high powers, which thynge, no man can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to you.<note place="margin">The Lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines &amp; Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptyſtes, do thynke no man to be a Chriſtyan, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept he recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth theyr doctryne and be baptized agayne.</note> For ye thinke no man to be a chriſtyan, excepte he doth cleaue too you, and receyue youre doctryne, and at length be baptized again by you, though all theſe things be altogether repugnant to chriſtyan ſtatutes, and publyke lawes No tongue can expreſſe how bytter and venymouſe, or poyſoned railyngs, ye do here vomite and ſpue out againſt the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SI.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe thynges neuer plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>IOI.</speaker>
               <p>But yet they are done of them. They do pycke and gather certain bytter and greuous ſayinges oute of the pſalmes and prophetes, which afterwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des being learned without boke, they do vomite againſte the magyſtrates. Theſe
<pb facs="tcp:13656:56"/> thinges do pleaſe to ſtubburne &amp; diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient perſons,<note place="margin">The ſcripture doth call the iudges and magyſtrates gods, becauſe that they be here in the roume &amp; ſtede of god, who ſoeuer then doth ryſe or rayle agaynſt them, God ſhall punyſhe him extremly</note> where as gods word doth forbyd vs to raile againſt the gods (for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture doth ſo cal the magiſtrats and iudges) Peter doth liuely ſet theym furth, vnder the name of falſe prophetes, in his latter epiſtle, and .iii. chap. O Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zins (ſay they) the magiſtrate is no chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian, but yet be obedient vnto him. And thei their own ſelues wil not be obedient vnto him, in the leſte thing of the world. What ſhould I ſay? They go aboute to aboliſh and put downe all magiſtrates &amp; high powers, that ſo they may do, what ſoeuer they liſt. Paul ſaith: If thou wilt not feare the hygh power, do that which is iuſte, but they do fear the hygh power (for they go about to abolyſh and put it downe) ergo, they wyll do that which is euyll. They are then the felowes of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, the Gaulonite, and of Siba, the ſon of Bocheri, whych both for their hygh treaſon, were worthely put to death. Of Iudas the Galonit, ſe Ieſephus, in the xviii. boke of antiquityes, and firſt chap. Actes .v. chapter. He dyd ſtyrre ſedition emonge the people, which he ſeducynge with hope of liberty, did periſh at length
<pb facs="tcp:13656:56"/> wyth many. Of Siba thou ſhalt read, in the ſeconde of kynges, and .xx. Chapter. Suche ſedytyous perſonnes, are in the ſcriptures, called the chyldren of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial. Therfore, my Symon, if thou wylt folow my councel, thou ſhalt leaue this falſe opi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion, and afterwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſtycke to the truth, and be obedient to the Magiſtrates, and ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SIM.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed my mynd, therfore I wyll folowe thy councell.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprynted the third daye of Aprill.</p>
            <p>Anno. Do. 1551.</p>
            <p>¶ At Worceter in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hygh ſtrete, by Ihon Ofwen.</p>
            <p>¶ They be alſo to ſell at Shreweſbury.</p>
            <p>☞ <hi rend="italic">Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13656:57"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
